<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Several arguments for concessions and alterations in the common prayer, and in the rites and ceremonies of the Church of England in order to a comprehension / by a minister of the Church of England, as by law established.</title>
            <author>Minister of the Church of England.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1689</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 186 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 40 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A59372</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S2752</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R33871</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13586579</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13586579</idno>
            <idno type="VID">100559</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A59372)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 100559)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1048:8)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Several arguments for concessions and alterations in the common prayer, and in the rites and ceremonies of the Church of England in order to a comprehension / by a minister of the Church of England, as by law established.</title>
                  <author>Minister of the Church of England.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 72 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for John Salusbury ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>MDCLXXXIX [1689]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of England. --  Book of common prayer.</term>
               <term>Church of England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:100559:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:100559:1"/>
            <p>SEVERAL ARGUMENTS FOR Conceſſions and Alterations IN THE Common Prayer, AND IN THE RITES and CEREMONIES OF THE <hi>Church of England,</hi> IN ORDER TO A COMPREHENSION.</p>
            <p>By a Miniſter of the CHURCH of ENGLAND, As by Law Eſtabliſhed.</p>
            <q>
               <p>The particular Forms of <hi>Divine Worſhip,</hi> and the <hi>Rites</hi> and <hi>Ceremonies</hi> appointed to be uſed therein being things in their own Nature indifferent, and alterable, and ſo acknowledged, it is but reaſonable upon weighty and important Conſiderations, according to the various Exigency of Times and Occaſions, ſuch Changes and Alterations ſhould be made therein, as to thoſe in Authority ſhould from time to time ſeem either ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary or expedient.</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>In the Pref. to the Common Prayer.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>John Salusbury,</hi> at the Riſing <hi>Sun,</hi> near the <hi>Royal Exchange</hi> in <hi>Cornhil,</hi> MDCLXXXIX.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:100559:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:100559:2"/>
            <head>THE PREFACE.</head>
            <p>GOD hath wrought very graciouſly, and in an Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary manner, for the deliverance of this Church and State from Popery and Arbitrary Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer, in ſuch a way of Peace as other Ages can, ſcarce parallel. But <hi>Beneficium poſtulat Officium,</hi> God's great Goodneſs calls for ſome ſuitable return in the way of Love, Thankfulneſs, and Obedience. And no doubt but the Lord ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pects ſome Work that is Great and Excellent; ſomewhat wore than ordinary for the good of that Church, which he hath ſo wonderfully preſerved. And if you would know what we ſhall render unto the Lord for all his Benefits. What more? What better than for Proteſtants with one Heart and one Mouth to glorifie God the Father of all our Mercies, and to Worſhip him with one conſent. And oh that the All-wiſe God would inſpire this Great Council of the Nation with Wiſdom from above, what, and how to act effectually for this Bleſſed <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion: Which (as Mr. <hi>De L' Angle</hi> in his Letter to his Lordſhip, the Biſhop of <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don) will rejoyce Men and Angels, and bring down a Thouſand Bleſſings of Heaven and Earth upon thoſe that ſhall contribute the moſt unto it,</hi> 
               <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nreaſ. of Separ. p. <hi>424.</hi> It is to be hoped that the Glory of ſo Great and Good a Work will
<pb facs="tcp:100559:3"/>be due to our preſent Governours next under God. And ſince we are told in the Preface before the Common Prayer, that in the Reigns of ſeveral Princes of Bleſſed Memory ſince the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation, the Church upon juſt and weighty Conſiderations her thereunto moving, hath yielded to make ſuch Alterations in ſome particulars, as in their reſpective times were thought conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient. Therefore I have added Arguments for ſuch Conceſſions and Alterations in this Worſhip, as may be effectual in order to the Deſired <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion. Though I have had God's Glory for my end, yet I know no Mans Integrity in the Cauſe of God and of Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; nor the moſt unfeigned Deſires, and Endeavours for the good and Peace of Church and State, can exempt him from the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon fate, that attends things of this Nature, which are ſure to be unacceptable with ſome, if not paſs for an unpardonable Offence againſt the Church of <hi>England.</hi> If I knew that there were any thing, but Truth and Charity, I would blot it out. If it be poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible, and as much as in me lyeth, I would live peaceably with all Men.</p>
            <p>The Motives and Inducements to write were theſe:</p>
            <p>Firſt, A Zeal for God. God's Honour is intimately con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned in his Worſhip. What Soul that hath any ſenſe of God and Religion can bear ſo much diſhonour as is done to God in his Worſhip? Several caſting a contempt upon it by their un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>handſom Speeches, and ill Examples, prejudiced and prejudicing others againſt it. Many ſcarce look upon it as the Worſhip of God, and mind nothing leſs than to be devout in it. And ſince the Worſhip of God lies under contempt, or a great abuſe and unprofitableneſs in the performance of it, is there not reaſon to be offended at it. I am not ſatisfied, and cannot be ſatisfied without ſome endeavour to redreſs the Evil.</p>
            <p>Second Motive was a deſire to diſcharge this part of my Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſterial duty to my own, and the Peoples better Edification. Does the VVorld think it is nothing to Miniſters, that have a concern for the Peoples Souls to ſee how little this VVorſhip is
<pb facs="tcp:100559:3"/>done to Edifying? How great a guilt lies upon their Congregati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons upon that very account! Surely guilt enough to lay them low in miſery. And the ſenſe of this put me upon another Deſign, (which was firſt in my intention) a ſhort piece Argumenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive for Conformity to the Prayers. And therein firſt to ſatisfie Peoples Conſciences in a peaceable Submiſſion and Communion in this Worſhip, though they do not like every thing in it beſt. I urge, that they themſelves will not ſuffer their Children and Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants to leave their Worſhip in their Families, under pretence that anothers is better: But the Governours Authority over the ſeveral Families in the Nation reacheth as far as theirs in their own Family, in all things, Sin only excepted, ſo far as they may be obeyed without diſobeying God. Secondly, To excite them to a Devout uſe of the Prayers, with ſome Helps and Directions for their Edification in it. Thirdly, To keep them within the Bounds of Chriſtian Charity, towards thoſe that differ from us; as knowing that without Charity all is nothing worth. Time and Opportunity called for this firſt, though leſs ſtudied or accurate, and plain in its Language.</p>
            <p>Third Motive was a compaſſionate Concern for ſome, who have ſuffered much by the ſeverity of the Laws, and a deſire to prevent their future ſufferings. I know there are thoſe, that diſſent from this Worſhip, that would, very heartily would, if their Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences had been ſatisfied, have Conformed to it; If they did not, they knew they were like to pay for it: But by ſuch Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſions as to take them in, they will be ſafe for the future from fear of Trouble and Sufferings.</p>
            <p>Fourth Motive was a deſire to do my part towards the reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dying the Evils which have eventually followed the Act for <hi>Uniformity.</hi> And ſurely in an Age, that hath ſmarted ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much, as this hath done for Contentions about theſe Common-Prayers, it concerns every one to put to his helping hand. I ſhall conclude with a Pathetical and Affectionate Speech of that Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verend Prelate, Dr. <hi>Hall,</hi> who uſed to ſay, <hi>War with none
<pb facs="tcp:100559:4"/>but</hi> Rome <hi>and</hi> Hell, and was a true Son of Peace. <hi>Biſhop Hall's Works, p. 426.</hi>
               <q>But thou, O Lord! How long? How long ſhall thy poor Church ſee the Dear Sons of her Womb bleeding about theſe Apples of Strife? (Speaking of ſome things in the <hi>Common Prayers,</hi> Ceremonies eſpecially.) Ye, Men, Brethren, and Fathers help, for Gods ſake put to your hands for the quenching of theſe Common Flames: The one ſide by Humility and Obedience, the other by Compaſſion (<hi>i.e.</hi> to the weak and unſatisfied) both by Prayers and Tears, that ſo that Paſſage in <hi>His Majeſties Declaration</hi> may take Effect for Eſtabliſhing ſuch Laws, as ſhould make a good Agreement between the <hi>Church of England,</hi> and <hi>Proteſtant Diſſenters.</hi>
               </q> May that Agreement be in the Worſhip of God. The Great God of Heaven, and every True-hearted <hi>Proteſtant</hi> ſay <hi>Amen</hi> to it.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="arguments">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:100559:4"/>
            <head>Arguments for Conceſſions and Alterations in the Common-Prayer, and in the Rites and Ceremonies of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> in order to the deſired <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion in Worſhip.</head>
            <p>CErtainly that man is no friend to Church and State, who is an enemy to their Peace and Union in matters of Religion: For, as the Eminent Mr. <hi>Le Moyn</hi> of <hi>Holland</hi> ſaith, in his Letter to his Lordſhip, the preſent Biſhop of <hi>London,</hi> at the end of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nreaſonableneſs of Separation. <hi>In</hi> England <hi>the good of Church and State depends abſolutely upon <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion of the People in point of Religion, and one cannot there preſs an <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion too much:</hi> For there is never like to be an effectual Reformation of Peoples un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reformed Lives without an Union, when Conforming and Noncon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forming Miniſters may joyn together, encourage, and aſſiſt each other in that bleſſed work. And as to an Union, Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> in his Life and Death of Sir <hi>Matthew Hale,</hi> ſaith, 2 <hi>p.</hi> 19, 20. that the ſaid Judge told him, the only means to heal us was a new Act of Unifor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity. Therefore I ſhall apply my ſelf to the Governours of the Church that are Lawfully called, and have Authority to appoint and alter matters of this nature, reſpecting the Service and Worſhip of God. I ſhall in all Humility recommend to the Governours Conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration ſome Arguments for Conceſſions and Alterations in the Common Prayer; and then in the Rites and Ceremonies of the Church of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land:</hi> And to ſhow that I am not alone, and that it is not a project of my own, which hath no countenance or encouragement from others, I ſhall mention greater Names in favour of the ſame Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and urge their concurrence; and that ſhall be my firſt Plea.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:100559:5"/>
               <hi>Firſt Plea,</hi> For ſome Conceſſions and Alterations in this Worſhip, becauſe there are ſome things which, in the judgment of ſeveral emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent Conformiſts, may be altered without any detriment or diſhonour to the Church. Divers Reverend Biſhops and Doctors, in a Paper in Print, before the unhappy Wars in King <hi>Charles</hi> I. Reign, yielded to the laying aſide of the Croſs, and the making many material Alte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations; as the Archbiſhop of <hi>Armagh,</hi> the Biſhop of <hi>Lincoln,</hi> Dr. <hi>Prideaux,</hi> Dr. <hi>Ward,</hi> Dr. <hi>Brownrigg,</hi> Dr. <hi>Featly,</hi> met together by Order of the Lords, at the Biſhop of <hi>Lincolns</hi> in <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides ſome Innovations in Diſcipline given in) hinted their deſire of the <hi>Alteration</hi> of many things in the <hi>Book of Common-Prayer,</hi> as the Reading of the <hi>Pſalms</hi> according to the <hi>New Tranſlations;</hi> Leſſons of <hi>Canonical Scripture</hi> inſtead of the <hi>Apocrypha;</hi> leaving out the <hi>Hymn of Benedicite,</hi> and the ſaying <hi>Gloria Patri</hi> after every <hi>Pſalm;</hi> changing <hi>with my Body I thee Worſhip,</hi> into theſe, <hi>I give thee Power over my Body; I Abſolve</hi> thee in the <hi>Viſitation</hi> of the <hi>Sick</hi> into theſe, I pronounce thee <hi>Abſolved,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Grand Debate,</hi> p. 31.</p>
            <p>Again, the Biſhop of <hi>Armagh,</hi> p. 130, 131. from Dr. <hi>Barnard,</hi> to this effect; That for the healing of thoſe diſtractions and diviſions among Miniſters, and others, and the moderating of each extream, in relation to the uſe of the Liturgy, whereby there might be a return of that wiſhed for Peace and Unity, which of late years we have been ſtrangers to, he conceived ſome prudent and moderate accommodation might be thought of by wife men, in order to the continuance of the ſubſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial part, each ſide yielding ſomewhat after the example of St. <hi>Paul, Rom.</hi> 14. <hi>Idem, Directions about the Liturgy;</hi> After his Vindication of the Liturgy, yet it cannot be denied but that there are <hi>naevi in pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chro corpore;</hi> and as it were to be wiſhed that theſe were altered, ſo it were to be done without much noiſe.</p>
            <p>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. Upon the <hi>Ordinance againſt the Common Prayer, Sect.</hi> 4. Our publick Liturgy, or Forms of conſtant Prayers, muſt be aboliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and not amended in what upon free and publick advice might ſeem to ſober men inconvenient for matter or manner, to which I ſhould eaſily conſent. <hi>Idem,</hi> To the Prince of <hi>Wales;</hi> In this Church I charge you to perſevere, as coming neareſt to Gods Word, with ſome little amendment, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>King <hi>Charles</hi> the Seconds Declaration from <hi>Breda,</hi> 1660. Since we find ſome exceptions made againſt ſeveral things in the Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turgy, we will appoint an equal number of Divines, of both per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſions, to review the ſame, and to make ſuch alterations as ſhall
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:100559:5"/>be thought moſt neceſſary, and ſome additional Forms; and it ſhall be left to the Miniſter to chuſe one or other. In the mean time we deſire that Miniſters would read thoſe parts, againſt which there lie no exceptions; yet in compaſſion to thoſe that ſcruple it, our will and pleaſure is, that none be puniſhed or troubled for not uſing it, until it be effectually Reformed, as aforeſaid.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Biſhop of</hi> Corks <hi>Proteſtant Peacemaker,</hi> p. 29. What moſt of the Diſſenters would be at, (no Liturgy, no Epiſcopacy,) may not be, cannot be without Schiſm; we are ready to ſacrifice all we can otherwiſe to the publick peace and ſafety, <hi>Idem</hi> p. 33. But notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding what I have ſaid of the excellency, both of the Common-Prayers, and of Cathedral Performances, I do not conceive the altera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of an Expreſſion, or here and there of a whole Prayer or two by Law, or diſpenſing with ſome Ceremonies; I do not conceive, ſuch relaxation as this would break the Harmony and Beauty of our Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, or diſturb the Union and Peace of our Church. There are ſome Collects, and perhaps Rubricks too, which with all duty and ſubmiſſion, I humbly conceive might be altered for the better. <hi>Page</hi> 118, 119.</p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Hales</hi> in his Tract of <hi>Schiſm,</hi> p. 215. Propounds it as re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy to prevent Schiſm, to have all Liturgies, and publick Forms of Service ſo framed, as that they admit not of particular and pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate fancies, but contain only ſuch things in which all Chriſtians do agree: Prayer, Confeſſion, Thanksgiving, Reading of Scriptures in the moſt plain and ſimple manner, were matter enough to furniſh out a ſufficient Liturgy, though nothing either of private Opinion, or of Church Pomp, of Garments, or preſcribed Geſtures, of Imagery, or Muſick, of matter concerning the Dead, of many ſuperfluities, which creep into the Church under the names of Order and Decency, did interpoſe it ſelf.</p>
            <p>The great Dean of St. <hi>Pauls</hi> in the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nreaſonableneſs of Separation,</hi> Pref. About the Book of Common-Prayer, it ought to be conſidered, whether for ſatisfaction of the ſcrupulous, ſome more doubtful and obſcure paſſages may not yet be explained, or amended? Whether the <hi>new Tranſlation</hi> of the <hi>Pſalms</hi> were not fitter to be uſed, eſpecially in <hi>Parochial Churches?</hi> Whether portions of <hi>Canonical Scripture</hi> were not better put inſtead of <hi>Apocrypha Leſſons?</hi> Whether the <hi>Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brick</hi> about the <hi>Salvation of Infants</hi> might not be reſtored to its for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer place, in the Office of <hi>Confirmation,</hi> and ſo the preſent excepti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:100559:6"/>againſt it be removed? Whether thoſe Expreſſions which ſuppoſe the ſtrict exerciſe of Diſcipline in <hi>Burying</hi> the <hi>Dead</hi> were not better left at <hi>Liberty</hi> in our preſent caſe? Such a review made by Wiſe and Peaceable Men, not given to wrath and diſputing, may be ſo far from being a diſhonour to this Church, that it may add to the glory of it.— And whether uſing the Liturgy, and Approbation and Promiſe of the uſe of it, may not be ſufficient inſtead of the late Form of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claring their Aſſent and Conſent, which hath been ſo much ſcrupled by our Brethren?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>True ſtate of the Primitive Church,</hi> p. 23. Now in Chriſt I hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly beſeech the Governours of the Church, calmly to conſider, were it not better to have ſuch a Form of Service as would ſatisfie moſt. The Fathers of our Church when they Reformed this Nation from Popery, were deſirous to fetch off as many as they could, retaining for this cauſe all the Ceremonies and Forms of Prayer they could, with a good rectified Conference. Some other things I could men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in the Book of Common-Prayer (though not ill in themſelves) yet fit to be altered, and would obviouſly appear to every wiſe man, once reſolved to compoſe ſuch a Form as to take in moſt of this Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; which I humbly conceive Governours ſhould in Conſcience en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour, becoming all things to all men to gain ſome, though not all, yet happily gain all in proceſs of time.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Principles and Practiſes of Moderate Divines,</hi> &amp;c. They would be very glad, if ſome things that moſt offend were taken out of the way, particularly, that there might be no expreſſions in our Forms of Prayer, that contain diſputable and uncertain Doctrine, <hi>p.</hi> 335. <hi>Vid.</hi> Mr. <hi>Wakes</hi> Sermon on <hi>Rom.</hi> 15.5, 6, 7. <hi>p.</hi> 23. And that no ſuch weight be laid on leſſer things, as that they ſhould be inſiſted on to the endangering thoſe of an higher nature, and hazarding the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches Proſperity and Peace.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Serious and Compaſſionate Enquiry into the cauſes</hi> &amp;c. That it will be no Hypocritical tergiverſation, no wrong either to our Religion, or our Conſciences, if when the caſe ſo requires it, we change any phraſe of Speech, how fit ſoever in our apprehenſion, for one leſs fit, but more acceptable and currant; or any Rite or Ceremony that we have great kindneſs for, for one that is more grateful unto others, and that according to the ſaying of the Lord <hi>Bacon,</hi> we learn of the elder times what is lawful, and of the preſent what is fitteſt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Mr.</hi> De L' Angels <hi>Letter to his Lordſhip, the preſent B. of</hi> London; I am
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:100559:6"/>ſure, that if there were nothing wanting to cure your Diviſions but the abſtaining from ſome Expreſſions, the quitting ſome Ceremonies, and the changing of the colour of ſome Habits, you would reſolve to do that, and ſomething more difficult than that with great pleaſure.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Conformiſts Plea for the Nonconformiſts,</hi> Part 3. Pref. It is clear there muſt be a Liturgy; and very many, even to Dr. <hi>Sherlock,</hi> mention ſome Alterations in the ſeveral parts of it, as deſirable and adviſable: Without any poſitive arrogance in a matter of this nature, I do offer my obſervation. Some that expect much profit by Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, do thing firſt and ſecond Service too long and tireſome: Others that care leſs for Preaching, are very buſie in the Interlocutory parts of the Service, grow careleſs, and too often prate (and ſtare about and whiſper) in the Leſſons, and ſleep under our Sermons; both are too long for them alſo. All that I will ſuggeſt in the laſt caſe is; Firſt, That the ſecond Service or Communion-Service, may be then only read, when there is a Communion, or when there is no Sermon [up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Holy-days]. Secondly, That only one of the three Creeds be uſed at one time, in the ſame Service. Thirdly, That the ſo often Repetitions of the Lords Prayer in the ſame Service may be limited. All cannot, moſt do not keep Curats: The work of Reading the ordinary firſt and ſecond Service, beſides incidental Offices, as Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm, Churchings, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> make it very expenſive to moſt mens Strength and Spirits, and weariſome to the People; and the conſtantineceſſary work of Preaching and Catechiſing is hardly endured by the young and healthful, but impoſſible to be performed by the infirm and aged. [And therefore in King <hi>Edward</hi> VI. day, ſome Miniſters were diſpenſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with in not Reading the whole, as <hi>Grand Debate</hi> mentions, <hi>p.</hi> 5.] It is true indeed if a mans Conſcience will bear it, a Miniſter may be both ſhort and ſeldom in the Pulpit; but the it is with two great hazards: Firſt, Of loſing his Auditory, or of his Auditories great loſs to their Souls. This humble Propoſal for omitting the ſecond Service, hath a fair Countenance from the Rubricks; Rubrick the laſt, immediately before the Lords Prayer hath a ſuppoſition that the Communion is Celebrated every Lords day, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I mean to conclude with an excellent Citation from Biſhop <hi>Taylor, Duct. Dubit.</hi> p. 375. In Rituals and Ceremonies, and little circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances of Eccleſiaſtical Offices, and Forms of Worſhip, in the pun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctualities of Rubricks, in the order of Collects, in the number of Prayers, and fulneſs of the Office upon a reaſonable cauſe, or induce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:100559:7"/>to the omiſſion or alteration; theſe things are ſo little, and fit to be entruſted to the conduct of thoſe ſober, obedient, and grave perſons, who are thought fit to be entruſted with the Cure of Souls: <q>And things of ſuch little concernment are ſo apt to yield to any wiſe mans reaſons, and ſudden occaſions, and accidents, and little and great Cauſes, that theſe were the fitteſt inſtances of this Rule (<hi>i. e.</hi> of Latitude) if Superiours would not make too much of little things. All juſt Governments give the largeſt interpretation to Churches Orders in theſe things, to perſons of a peaceable Mind and obedient Spirit, that ſuch circumſtances may not paſs into a ſolemn Religion; and the Zeal of good Men, their Caution and Curioſity may not be ſpent in that which doth not profit. In many caſes a Latitude according to Equity may be preſumed;</q> but if it be expreſly denied it may not be uſed: Which is the caſe of our Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formiſts as to thoſe things, wherein a Latitude might be taken accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Law of Equity, when they carry ſome conſiderable incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venience along with them, and reaſon for the contrary; yet we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſtrictly bound up by the Church, it muſt bring a guilt upon the perſons, diſturb their peace of Conſcience, and prove vexatious and troubleſome to them that way, if they often offend in theſe matters. And this I preſume to be the caſe of thoſe, who in their common pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice do not come up to the ſtrictneſs of their bounden and promiſed Conformity, though in ſome caſes, when <hi>extra caſum ſcandali &amp; contemptus,</hi> they may do otherwiſe than the expreſs Letter of the Law requires, and be guiltleſs, as our Caſuiſts affirm.</p>
            <p>I beg the favour with all Humility, and with Submiſſion to the Will and Wiſdom of our Governours, to offer to their Conſideration; whether it were not deſirable to have a Prayer for particular Graces in the Evening Service, (the Petitioning part being leſs perfect then) and at ſuch times when the Letany is not uſed. We have ſuch a Prayer in the <hi>Whole Duty of Man,</hi> called a Prayer for Grace, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſive of particular Graces. And then no doubt the uſe of it would be more acceptable in Families than it is now, when it runs out ſo much in Interceſſions, and ſo little in Petition.</p>
            <p>Again I offer to their Conſideration; whether the Hymns and Offices of Praiſe after the Leſſons, (eſpecially in the Evening Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice) are not become leſs edifying in their preſent uſe, where thoſe Spiritual Songs are barely Read, (as in Pariſh Churches) and not Sung; <hi>there being one way of Singing,</hi> or an Harmonious Reading of
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:100559:7"/>them uſeful and edifying, though another way not ſo much to Edification, becauſe out few underſtand it in the way of an An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>them. There are ſome things of particular reſpect to the Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> and good Old <hi>Symeon,</hi> not ſo ſuitable to the Congregation. Whither the Wiſdom of our Governours may not ſee reaſon to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bear thoſe Anthems wholly in <hi>Pariſh Churches,</hi> or to leave the uſe of them indifferent, or limit them <hi>pro hic &amp; nunc,</hi> according as times of Joy and Victory require our Praiſe, or other times of Humiliation to forbear them.</p>
            <p>One thing more I beg leave to offer; If our Governours ſee reaſon to alter any thing in the Baptiſmal Office, about the ſign of the Croſs, Sureties, or elſewhere; whether it were not deſirable to have ſome ſuch Scriptures inſerted, as <hi>Job</hi> 25.4.14.4. <hi>How can he be clean that is born of a Woman: Who can bring a clean thing out of an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clean;</hi> that parents may ſee their Childrens Condition ſince the fall, defil'd with Sin, polluted and unclean; and ſo their great need of the Grace of Baptiſm, to be waſhed and cleanſed through the Blood of Chriſt from their Natural pollution and defilement by Sin. If this were but clearly expreſſed, and well underſtood, as it would be one of the ſtrongeſt Arguments for Infant Baptiſm from their Childrens need of the Baptiſmal Grace, ſo it would be a good preſervative againſt Anabaptiſm.</p>
            <p>And as to the General Thankſgiving, perhaps it were to be deſired, that to the Redemption by Jeſus Chriſt, and the Means of Grace, were added, and for the Spirit of Grace ſanctifying an Holy Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Church, and for the Forgiveneſs of Sins which we believe and hope for, and the Reſurrection of the Body unto Eternal Life. Some have thought our Thankſgiving too general, in that there is no men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion made in it of Sanctification. If any of theſe things approve it ſelf unto our Governours, my Labour is not loſt. Out of this variety I doubt not, but that their Wiſdom knows what to chuſe, as ſhall be moſt for God's Glory, and the Churches Edification.</p>
            <p n="2">II. <hi>Arg.</hi> For Conceſſions and Alterations in the <hi>Common Prayer,</hi> becauſe that Worſhip according to the Acts for Uniformity, or the exceeding ſtrictneſs of the Enjoyn'd Conformity to it, hath been occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſionally, or at leaſt eventually Evil.</p>
            <p>Firſt, In reſpect of our Unchriſtian Diviſions and Separation. Thoſe that diſlike this Worſhip, (as there have been ſuch from the Diviſions in Queen <hi>Maries</hi> dayes at <hi>Frankford</hi>) and refuſe to joyn in
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:100559:8"/>it, whether do they uſually betake themſelves but to ſeparating, and ſetting up another Worſhip? Even thoſe that will joyn with the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter in his own Prayers, and his Sermon, yet ſeparate from the Common Prayers above any other Worſhip. Hence are ſo many Sects and Opinions among us, that our Nation is ſcandalous upon that account among other Proteſtants, who have a common ſaying, <hi>Half</hi> England is not of the Church of <hi>England.</hi> Good God ! What would become of Peace and Union, Love and Charity, if the next Age ſhould be as fruitful of Sects and Parties, and differ in their Modes of Worſhip, as much, as the preſent hath done, wherein thy Church hath been ſo miſerably divided? How long, O Lord, the Author of Peace, and Lover of Concord, wil't thou ſuffer ſuch Confuſion in the Churches of the Saints.</p>
            <p n="2">2. This Worſhip, with the <hi>Penal Laws</hi> Eccleſiaſtical and Civil, that inforced the Act for <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niformity,</hi> hath been occaſionally, or at leaſt eventually evil, by bringing hard ſuffering upon the contrary-minded. Many formerly choſe rather to leave their Native Country, and ſhelter themſelves in <hi>New-England,</hi> than endure the Severities then, and Conventions before the High Commiſſion Court. And if I ſhould ſpeak of the Preſentments and Excommunications, the Fining, Impriſoning, and Confinement from Corporations in latter years, it would be no more pleaſing to ſome to hear of them, than it was to others to ſuffer them. Ah how harſh did theſe things ſound in the Ears of Merciful Men, and the Reformed Churches abroad, that Proteſtants ſhould be worrying one another, biting and devouring one another, and doing the Enemies work for him, who ſcornfully rejoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced at it, and uſed to ſay, Give the Hereticks Rope enough, and they would hang themſelves. But Bleſſed be God who hath taken away the occaſion of theſe Evils, and done that effectually by the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Parliament which the Preceeding would have done, as we are informed in the Memorial from the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Proteſtants to His Highneſs the Prince of <hi>Orange, p.</hi> 28. Four of our Succeeding Parliaments perceived the abuſe of theſe <hi>Penal Laws,</hi> and the miſchief thereby to Conſcious Chriſtians; and declared their intention of relieving them, if the King would have permitted them, yet they endeavoured to ſtop the Execution of them, and deſired a Settlement of Liberty of Conſcience as is due to Chriſtians. Adieu now to theſe Preſentments, Fines, Impriſonments, Excommunications, Troubling the Peace of our Neighbours, and too often it hath been our peaceable Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours;
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:100559:8"/>though I am apt to think but few have ſuffered comparatively with the many that eſcaped, yet thoſe that ſuffered, were too many, and to be pitied; ſeveral of them as honeſt, well-meaning Perſons, though miſlead through weakneſs of Judgment, and ſcruples of Conſcience.</p>
            <p n="3">3. This Worſhip conſidered with the Acts for Uniformity, hath been occaſionally, or at leaſt eventually Evil, in reſpect of the War and Miſeries in King <hi>Charles</hi> the Firſt his dayes, occaſioned much, if not beginning by the Impoſition of the Liturgy on <hi>Scotland,</hi> for an Union of both Nations in Worſhip. That Nation was ſo much in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſed that they drove, or were ready to drive the Miniſters out of their Churches at the reading of it; and broke out into a Rebellion, which infected <hi>England</hi> with their Covenant to down with the Litur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy, and Biſhops.</p>
            <p n="4">4. This Worſhip by the exceeding ſtrictneſs of the Acts for Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity, Subſcriptions, Aſſent and Conſent, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> hath been an occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion why ſo many Diſſenting Miniſters of conſiderable Gifts and Graces have been rendred in a great meaſure unſerviceable to the Church by, Suſpenſion, or Deprivation.</p>
            <p>Some in Queen <hi>Elizabeths</hi> time, when (as the <hi>Reverend Dean of St.</hi> Paul<hi>'s</hi> ſaith in his <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nreaſ. of Separation,</hi>) they could very ill be ſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, not to ſpeak of thoſe in King <hi>James</hi> the Firſt his Reign, and King <hi>Charles</hi> the Firſt; of later years, as the return of King <hi>Charles</hi> the Second, a great Number of Miniſters, Good and Worthy Men in the main, and for the generality of them, were deprived for their Nonconformity.</p>
            <p n="5">5. This Worſhip hath been eventually Evil, by weakning the hands of Diſcipline, while the ſcandalous open evil Livers have eſca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped the Cenſures of the Church, together with the more peaceable, and innocently-minded Separatiſts. Thus <hi>Dr. Cumber on the Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation Service,</hi> Diſcipline with-held <hi>(ſaith he)</hi> in favour of Diſſenters, leſt by impoſing of it there, this Holy Means of Reformation ſhould be deſpiſed, rather than obeyed. And ſhould Men have gone about to ſuppreſs and reform Debauchery and Prophaneneſs by a ſtrict Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentation of them, the Court, which hath more hotly purſued the Diſſenters, than the Scandalous and Vicious, would like enough have put them upon Preſentment of Diſſenters, without any favour or dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference between the weak and the wilful; which becauſe of the ill Conſequence (which too often followed) Excommunication and Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſonment,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:100559:9"/>many Miniſters and Church-Wardens were more back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward and averſe unto. Their Conſciences would not ſuffer them to work ſuch ill and trouble to their Chriſtian Brethren, Fellow Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants, Loving Neighbours, for ſome ſmall difference in leſſer mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters not deſtructive of their Salvation. And no doubt but the Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of our Governours ſaw the Evil and Inconvenience of thoſe ſeverities. When they took away the <hi>Penal Laws</hi> that made the <hi>Common Prayer,</hi> and Act for <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niformity</hi> ſo terrible to the contrary-minded.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Arg.</hi> 3. For Proof that the Common Prayer, according to the Acts for Uniformity, is inconvenient in ſome reſpect, and may ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit of Alteration, becauſe of the great diſguſts, and almoſt invincible prejudices of People, (eſpecially in the Country) againſt this Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, or at leaſt ſome things therein Cars <hi>Peaceable Moderator, or Plain Conſiderations for ſatisfaction to the diſaffected to our Common-Prayers.</hi> In the Preface, many ſtumble much at our Book of <hi>Common Prayers;</hi> and ſome of them, I take to be good Chriſtians, honeſt, moderate, well-meaning People, and have found by experience much of their diſaffection to it doth lye upon their miſtake through Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, not peeviſh wilfulneſs. After all our Preaching and Inſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and Exhortations in behalf of the <hi>Common Prayer,</hi> we do not find that ſucceſs which we uſe to have in other matters, and which we might expect, if their prejudice were not ſo deeply rooted in them, and too mighty for us. The difficulty is great, becauſe the guilt of People is great. Where People have often ſinned any Sin, the harder it is to repent: And how often have may been preſent at theſe Prayers? Yet, I fear, ſcarce ever prayed heartily and acceptably. Again, Sins deſcending from Parents to their Children, are harder to be worked out of them; but prejudices againſt this Worſhip have been tranſmitted down from Parents, and as it were entailed upon ſome Families: So that there is as little hopes of gaining them over, as for bringing Men off from the Religion of their Anceſtours; which com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly proves unſucceſsful.</p>
            <p>Again the Commonneſs of this Guilt, were it but two or three in a Congregation that were prejudiced againſt it, there were the more hopes, that by the Examples of others they might be recovered: But when it is a great, (if not the greater) part of the Congregation, that is not heartily reconciled to this Worſhip (as I fear it is in too many Pariſhes.) It is the greater difficulty, when the Diſeaſe is ſo gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:100559:9"/>when the Infection hath ſpread it ſelf ſo much, to cure it effectually.</p>
            <p>There is too much proof of Peoples prejudices, in that the number is ſo ſmall, ſo few that come to the Prayers upon the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Dayes; and yet the Church is ſo exceedingly full at a Funeral Sermon, (or any other preaching time,) when People are not much longer at Church than on ſome Holy Dayes And on the Lord's Day there are few that will come to the Prayers, to be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent at the whole Service, many hard Speeches againſt them, ſome reviling them, as the Maſs-Book, Popiſh, Superſtitious will Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, Prayers of courſe a cold dead piece of Formality. There are ſo many Objections, Scruples, and Cavils againſt it, as dull and tedious for the length of it; as a Form of others making, and not the Miniſters own; as Book-Prayers ſlighted by the vulgar upon that account, who ſay they can read the <hi>Common Prayer</hi> as well as the Parſon,; againſt the Reſponſes, though uſed among the <hi>Jews</hi> and <hi>Primitive Chriſtians;</hi> againſt the ſhort Prayers, and Hymns read (and not ſung,) diſuſed both in our other Devotions, more common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly but one continued Prayer without ony intermixture; againſt ſome things cenſured as vain Repetitions; and againſt the Ceremonies uſed in the Worſhip. As to particular exceptions you may find enough, if not more than enough in the Grand Debate between the Conformiſts and Nonconformiſts: How theſe prejudices may be in a great mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure abated and taken away, I ſhall ſhow as the benefit of Union, That a Comprehenſion of the more ſober and moderate Diſſenters might do it in time.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Evils of this Prejudice.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, It is the cauſe of the ſcandalous abuſe and profanation of Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Dayes. If People were unprejudiced, an Hour ſpent in devout Prayer and praiſes, due Attention unto the Word of God, and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time in good inſtruction of Youth, and Explication upon the Church-Catechiſme, or Expoſition of the Epiſtle and Goſpel of the Day, would turn to ſome good account; and the <hi>Evening Service</hi> uſed to, as appointed on Holy Dayes; but prejudice mars and hinders all this from taking effect, and makes our Holy-Dayes uſeleſs in many Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhes, a loſs and hindrance rather than advantage to Religion.</p>
            <p>Secondly, It hath occaſioned much diſhonour to God on the Lord's Day. Firſt, By a great neglect of this Worſhip, ſeveral abſenting from it, and ſtaying till the Prayers are over before they come, and
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:100559:10"/>loſing the benefit of this Worſhip wholly; which is commonly the bigger half of God's Worſhip on the Forenoons, and the whole Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice of God in many Pariſhes in the Afternoon, there being no Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, nor Catechiſing, nor at leaſt no Explication of Catechiſme. And is it nothing for ſo many People in many Pariſhes to loſe the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit of half God's ſolemn Worſhip? No doubt but they are highly guilty before God, and will be found ſo at that day, when Sins which the World counts light of, ſhall appear in their juſt weight of Guilt according to the Word of God. Again Secondly, It occaſions much diſhonour to God on his own day, by reaſon of Peoples great unprofitableneſs in this Duty; many preſent at it, manifeſting ſuch a careleſs Spirit, as if they were not worſhipping God; doing any thing rather than that: Some waiting with great impatience, until the Prayers be at an end, as if there were no good to be gotten by them. How is it to be expected, that it ſhould be done to edifying, until Peoples prejudices be removed? That their Hearts ſhould be right and devout in a Worſhip, which their minds are not reconcil'd unto? They muſt be brought to ſome good liking of it, as a true and ſound Worſhip of God, ſuch as God will own, before they will ſerve God with the internal Acts of Devotion, be Spiritual and acceptable with him in his Worſhip. And if it be little to you to neglect this Worſhip, or loſe the benefit of it when you do perform it heartleſly, praying as if you pray'd not, and ſo you may expect that God ſhould hear as if he heard not, and give you a cold Anſwer to ſuch cold and faint Requeſts: And it is to be feared, that the lukewarmneſs and indifferency of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny (not the worſt of Chriſtians) in this Worſhip will hardly conſiſt with their Everlaſting Welfare, much leſs attain the ends of Devotion. Thirdly, Conſider further, That this great abuſe of God's VVor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, and unprofitable performance of it, is like to be an hindrance to you, as to God's Bleſſing on the remaining Duties: And will that do no hurt, if the Prayers (as ſome think) will do no good? VVe are forbid to <hi>quench the Spirit</hi> and his Grace: Imagine we Men to be war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med and fervent in Spirit, and in frame for Holy things at their firſt coming to Church, this Heavenly warmth and zeal muſt needs be quenched and cooled by their dull and dead-hearted formality in this VVorſhip.</p>
            <p>You know, one Sin <hi>grieves the Holy Spirit,</hi> and makes him withdraw further from us: One Duty careleſly and negligently performed makes
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:100559:10"/>him the more unwilling to aſſiſt in other duties. They that regard not the Word read, God will regard them the leſs in the Word prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched. They that give not God the Honour in his Praiſes due to his Name, God will regard their Prayers the leſs: And if your firſt pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the publick Prayers be turned into Sin, ſhall not their latter Service be leſs acceptable with him, than if every Duty and every Service were performed in a Spiritual manner to Edifying?</p>
            <p>Again Thirdly, The Peoples Prejudice and ill Opinion of ſome things in this Worſhip does work in them an ill Opinion of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernours in Church and State, who enjoyn them. They are ready to think, that the Governours have little care and concern for the good of their Souls, little regard to their Edification, who continue thoſe things which in their Judgments are no edifying, and their continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance notwithſtanding all the Objections and Exceptions againſt them.</p>
            <p>Again Fourthly, Their prejudice hindereth them from diſcerning what is good, or uſeful, and excellent, in the <hi>Common Prayer,</hi> and diſpoſeth them on the contrary to cavil, and find fault with it, in what is inconvenient, to gather the doubtful and obſcure paſſages, and to ſtretch every thing to the worſt ſenſe, even beyond the intention and deſign of them, when a good liking and approbation of it would diſpoſe them to judge Charitably; and <hi>Charity,</hi> you know, <hi>covers a multitude of leſſer faults.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Cure of theſe Prejudices. I doubt not, but that (by the Bleſſing of God) ſuch Conceſſions and Alterations in the <hi>Common Prayers,</hi> as to take in our Diſſenting Brethren (as certainly the more ſober and moderate Miniſters of the Presbyterian Perſwaſion would come in upon ſome Conceſſions) would weaken much Peoples Scruples and Objections againſt the Prayers. For we know, <hi>non minus exempla trahunt quam. praecepta docent,</hi> the People are lead by the Example of their Teachers, as much, as by their Doctrines: When they ſhall find the ableſt Miniſters among the Diſſenters to read, and conform to it in their Practice, and in their Preaching to defend and vindicate it, exhort and perſwade others to conform thereunto, (as even the Old Nonconformiſts, not to the Prayers, but to the Ceremonies, and the ſubſcription by <hi>Canon,</hi> uſed to do) the People (at leaſt in ſome conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable meaſure) may come to be convinced of their Errour in the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſteem
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:100559:11"/>of theſe Prayers; Beſides, that their Prejudices, Opinionative Conceits, and Scruples will fall of themſelves, when the things that offend them are taken out of the way. Then People will profit more, when prejudice is abated, and be aſhamed to carry themſelves ſo negligently, and contemptuouſly, as before; and the whole Worſhip of God, the Prayers and Office of the Desk as well as of the Pulpit be done to Edifying, not claſhing one againſt another, nor contending for the Pre-eminence; Holy-Dayes of the Churches appointment by that means will be more improved, as Peoples prejudices againſt the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice ſhall ceaſe or decay; and we may hope to ſee the Lord worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped in the Beauty of Holyneſs, and ſomewhat like the Zeal and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votion, Grace and Spirit which the Primitive Chriſtians manifeſted in their Forms of Prayer: Whereas now we bear only or chiefly a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity to them in the External Modes of our Worſhip, while we have loſt the inward Life, and keep the Form of their Godly Prayers without that Power and Spiritual Affection which they had; as <hi>Tertullian</hi> tells us, <hi>Beſieging God with their Prayers,</hi> as it were pier<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing the Heavens to the Throne of Grace, doing Violence unto it, to take Heaven, or Heavenly and Spiritual Bleſſings by force. We are told too, how forward the Primitive Chriſtians uſed to be, and earneſt to be preſent at the beginning of their Worſhip, with Sighs and Tears in their Eyes, manifeſting their Internal and unfeigned Devotion. And if Peoples prejudices ſhould once be overcome, and they come to any good Appetite to this Spiritual Food, they would be as ſure to come to the beginning of God's VVorſhip, as commonly they do to the beginning of a Feaſt, or at leaſt few that will ſtay until that is over before they come; and few that would loſe the benefit of ſo much of God's VVorſhip, as they do by coming late, and worſhipping God in an outward lifeleſs way, without an inward Conformity; which is the unhappineſs of our times, and is never like to be remedied while Peoples prejudices continue, and the things that they diſguſt, as the length of the Prayers, the often uſe of the Lord's Prayer, the Sign of the Croſs, Reading the Second Service at the Communion Table, or Altar, with bowing towards it, Godfathers, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Arg.</hi> 3. For Alteration in the Prayers is from the difference of the preſent Caſe, from that at the Reformation.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:100559:11"/>
Firſt, This Worſhip, conſidered with the ſeveral Forms, Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> was more neceſſary then, when the Miniſters were very ignorant, (many of them) and more fit to read others Sermons, (as they did the Homilies with profit) and to uſe others Prayers, that either to make Sermons or Prayers of their own. They were ſo ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant, that it was complained, ſome of them could ſcarce Read, and many of them did not underſtand Latin; and then a Form of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers making, ſound in Doctrine and Worſhip, was profitable, if not neceſſary, leaſt they ſhould have put in Errors or Hereſies into their own Prayers: For they would have made very pitiful ſtuff, ſorry matter of it, if they were to have made any long Prayer of their own, though a Form. But now there is more Light and Knowledge in theſe days, (to give that Argument a juſt weight) inſomuch, that if Miniſters be not very idle and negligent, ſo many good Books of Devotion, and excellent pieces of Divinity, as the Church of Chriſt abounds with, they may be able to make ſuch Prayers, as may be ſound and comprehenſive, ſuitable and edifying: Nay, they may at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain to ſome ability to expreſs their deſires to God without an exact Form, if they are ſuch perſons as are much in the practice of this Duty, as it is fit Miniſters ſhould be, after the example of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, <hi>Acts</hi> 6.4. <hi>But we will give our ſelves continually to Prayer, and the Miniſtry of the Word.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, It was more ſeaſonable at the Reformation than another Worſhip; becauſe it receded leaſt from their former Worſhip, leaving that only in what was plainly and undoubtedly evil; and ſo was it more ſafe upon the ſame account. For it is a common Rule in all Changes in Bodies Natural and Political, that the Change be no more then needs muſt, it being dangerous to run from one extream into another: And that Change which they did make in the Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, was no without its danger; for in <hi>Devonſhire</hi> and <hi>Cornwall</hi> there was a Rebellion upon the account of changing their Worſhip: But there would be no danger of Rebellion now upon ſome juſt alte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations. It cauſed one indeed in <hi>Scotland</hi> (as before) which infected <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, It was more ſatisfactory and acceptable to the genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of the Nation, at the time of the Reformation, than any other. So that we do not read of any that ſeparated from it in <hi>Edward</hi> VI.
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:100559:12"/>days. And though, when they were at liberty in <hi>Germany,</hi> ſome were for another Worſhip at <hi>Frankford,</hi> yet we do not read, but they Conformed to it in <hi>England,</hi> until near the <hi>Spaniſh Invaſion,</hi> when a party of <hi>Jeſuits</hi> and <hi>Roman Prieſts</hi> were found crying up a ſort of Free Prayer, drawing ſome off from the Common-Prayer, though not men of note. And in the Act, <hi>Primo Elizabethae,</hi> you may find the eſteem they had for this Worſhip: It ſaith, to the great decay of the due Honour of God, and diſcomfort to the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſors of the Truth of Chriſts Religion, the Common-Prayer Book, and the Act for it was repealed and taken away in Queen <hi>Maries</hi> days. But now the generality of Diſſenters, and many that follow the Pariſh Miniſters are diſſatisfied in it; and have little or no liking to it; and whatever is the matter, the genius of the people will not bear it, or ſome things in it; or at leaſt not otherwiſe then as a Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then and a Grievance.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Arg.</hi> IV. For proof that the Common-Prayer, according to the <hi>Acts for <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niformity,</hi> is inconvenient in ſome reſpects; becauſe of the confinement of Miniſters to the uſe of it, not only in the publick, but in their Families, in a manner wholly excluding all other manner of Prayer, even the moſt ſober and diſcreet uſe of the Gift, as <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon the Ordinance againſt the Common-Prayer Book,</hi> Sect. 4. I am not againſt a grave, modeſt, diſcreet, and humble uſe of Miniſters gifts, even in publick, the better to excite their own, and the peoples affections to the preſent occaſions. Again, upon de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nying him his Chaplains, <hi>Sect.</hi> 16. Which gift as I do not wholly ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude from publick occaſions, ſo I allow it its juſt liberty, and uſe in private and devout retirements.</p>
            <p>And the <hi>Act for <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niformity,</hi> in the beginning of King <hi>Edwards</hi> Reign, did give Liberty to uſe any other Prayers and Pſalms, taken out of the Bible, at any due time, not letting or omitting thereby the Service, or any part thereof. More may be ſpoken to enforce this part, that Miniſters ſhould labour after ſome meaſure of the gift and ability to utter their minds to God in Prayer, without keeping ſtrictly to a Form.</p>
            <p>Firſt, Ejaculatory Prayer calls for ſome meaſure of this gift, as when we lift up our Hearts to God upon any preſent occaſion in ſome
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:100559:12"/>ſhort Prayer; as in time of Temptation, upon ſudden Danger, or news of the Sickneſs or Death of a Friend, or Judgment or Mercy befalling the Nation, or Pariſh in which we live; or according to the Diſcourſe and Company which we are in, or matter which we read. <hi>Biſhop</hi> Taylor <hi>in his Rules to his Clergy; That they ſhould teach their People to be much in this Ejaculatory Prayer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, For ſome gift and ability to Pray without a Form is, becauſe that Examination of our Hearts and Lives upon ſet days of Faſting and Humiliation before a Sacrament, and in times of Affliction and Sickneſs, or any Calamity; the dayly Examination alſo accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to many ſober Heathens practice, <hi>Pythagoras</hi> his Advice to his Scholars to that purpoſe; and which is the practice of good men, and ſerves only to find out our ſins, that we may beg pardon of them, and power againſt them, or be thankful to God for his Grace, keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing us from ſin, or enabling us to do good, and this cannot be done in one ſet Form.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, Miniſters Sermons ſhould be begun, continued, and end<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with Prayer. Prayer for Direction to a ſuitable Subject, ſuch as the neceſſities of the people call for Method, Matter, Language, that all may be done to edifying: And when it is finiſhed, it is fitting to recommend it unto God, for his Bleſſing upon it. The more Prayer, the more power working with our Sermons. You will find ſuch Sermons take moſt effect, they will be weak without it. And after Preaching, that the Word Preached may be put in practice. Some Miniſters in the Country having a ſhort Prayer after Sermon, reſpect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the principal matter of the Sermon, as the Duties, Graces, Truths of our Chriſtian Religion, or Sins; as 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.16. <hi>The Word being profitable for Doctrine,</hi> Reproof, to convince Gainſayers; for Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection and Amendment of evil Manners, and for Inſtruction in Righteouſneſs or Holineſs, by an exerciſe of the Graces, perform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of the Duties of our Religion: Now Prayer muſt accompany all the Ordinances of God to ſanctifie, and get Gods Bleſſing on them.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, It is fit that all ſhould vary in their Prayers, ſo much as occaſions ſerves, our Sins, our Wants, our Mercies: Neither thoſe of the Nation, nor a particular Congregation, are the ſame always,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:100559:13"/>not altogether, though much the ſame. Therefore it is fit our Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titions, Interceſſions, and Thankſgivings ſhould admit of ſome alte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Arg.</hi> V. For ſome ability to pray without an exact Form is, that in <hi>Phil.</hi> 4.6. <hi>In every thing by Prayer and Supplication with Thanks<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giving let your Requeſts be made known unto God:</hi> In every thing of great concernment and importance in our Lives, be it Worldly or Spiritual matters. Beſides, in the two firſt Centuries this ſort of Prayer prevailed in all probability, and a mixt Worſhip in the third, partly by Form, and part otherwiſe.</p>
            <p>'Tis too apparent to be denied, and hath been the obſervation of too many, and their complaint too, that Miniſters take occaſion from the uſe of the Common-Prayers to neglect the ſober uſe of free and conceived Prayer, being inſufficient to pray upon an emergent occaſion, to the ſcandal of their Function, and deriſion of Diſſenters. If one unexpectedly light upon a ſick perſon, and be deſired to pray for him, it is a pitiful excuſe for him to ſay he hath not his Book with him. In caſe of any Calamity befalling a Pariſh; Fire, any Infectious Diſeaſe, or much Sickneſs, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Or any National Judgment, as upon poor <hi>Ireland,</hi> or Mercy, as the Miracle of Mercy and Deliverance wrought for us of this Nation, it will be expected, or at leaſt it is fit that Miniſters ſhould put in Occaſional Expreſſions for ſuch matters; elſe it will be look'd up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on on as a weakneſs, and uncomfortable failing in them, not to be able to ſay a Word, or put in an Expreſſion in things of ſuch Importance and Concernment to the Congregation, which remain many times un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>provided for by the Common-Prayers.</p>
            <p>Firſt, The length of the Common-Prayers allows little room for, the exerciſe of the gift in publick, though it be with Sobriety and Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration. So much of the time paſſeth in the uſe of this Worſhip, that there is little remaining, when the Sermon takes up ſo much beſides.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Many in Cathedrals, Viſitations, and often in their Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh Churches uſe only the Lords Prayer in the Pulpit, conſidering the length of their Common-Prayers: And indeed a long Prayer in the Pulpit, after the long Prayers of the Desk, ſeems to me to be highly inconvenient for the Common-Prayer, caſting a diſreſpect upon that;
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:100559:13"/>whereas if the Miniſters own Prayer were placed after the Sermon, to pray for a Bleſſing upon the practical matter of the Sermon among other things, it would much further Miniſters Gift and Ability in Prayer, and promote Gods Bleſſing upon the Word. In Duties preached to pray for Grace to perform them; Graces, that they may be wrought in us; Truths, (ſuch as are without Controverſie) for Grace to know and believe them Spiritually; and Grace to repent of ſins, or keep from them, with a Confeſſion and Thankſgiving for Mercies Spiritual or Temporal.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, The <hi>Canon bidding Prayer,</hi> taken in a ſtrict ſence, ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth utterly to forbid and diſallow of all uſe of the gift in publick. Therefore by ſome Conformiſts it is condemned, and held utterly unlawful for them, to uſe any other than an exact Form in generals according to that Canon.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, Some look upon themſelves bound to uſe the Common-Prayers, and no others in their Families, according to <hi>that Order;</hi> All Prieſts and Deacons are to ſay daily the Morning and Evening Prayer, either privately or openly, not being let by Sickneſs, or ſome other urgent cauſe. And the Curate, not being reaſonably hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered, ſhould ſay the ſame in the Pariſh-Church: So that if it be not ſaid openly in the Pariſh Church, if Sickneſs or ſome other ur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent cauſe do not hinder, it is to be ſaid privately in their Families, or perſonally by a mans ſelf.</p>
            <p>Fifthly, Some Conformiſts ſo addicted to this Form in their Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies, and in publick, are ſo ſet againſt all other manner of Prayer, as to call it <hi>ex tempore</hi> Effuſion, Confuſion, vain Bablings, Non-ſenſe, running beyond the very heighth of Conformity. Far be it from me to plead for, or to excuſe and countenance the wild extravagancies of ſome fanciful Spirits, who place their Devotion more in their various modes of ſpeaking to God, and expreſſing the matter of their Prayers rather than in the Truth and Piety of the Heart: Yet I think we ought, with Biſhop <hi>Wilkins,</hi> to endeavour after the Gift of Prayer; accordingly to exerciſe it in thoſe caſes above-mentioned: And per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps ſome more liberty in publick were deſirable, or at leaſt the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe of that liberty, which ſome ſuppoſe given us already; as <hi>Cars Plain Conſiderations for ſatisfaction to the diſaffected to our Book of
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:100559:14"/>Common-Prayer,</hi> p. 8. Our Miniſters have liberty, not only in pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate, but in publick, both before and after their Sermons, to exerciſe their Gift of Prayer, and to enlarge themſelves upon any emergent occaſion or opportunity afforded, as God ſhall enable them, and they themſelves ſhall judge any way expedient or needful. <hi>Caſes of Conſcience of the Lawfulneſs of joyning with Forms of publick Prayer,</hi> Part 1. p. 28. <q>The Clergy of the Church of <hi>England</hi> are not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained from exerciſing their own abilities in publick Prayer; in which is allowed them the liberty the Diſſenting Miniſters can claim or pretend to, to expreſs in their own words all the matter of publick Prayer, with all the ſobriety, affection and ſeriouſneſs they are able. And this permiſſion being of long continuance, and hitherto uncontrouled by our Church-Governours amounts to an allowance.</q>
               <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Such a liberty as this, and ſuch a practice con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>current with it were deſirable: But all are not agreed herein, nor ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied in point of this liberty.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Arg.</hi> 6. For Conceſſions and Alterations in the Common Prayer, becauſe of the frequent commands of bearing with the infirmities of the weak, (<hi>i. e.</hi> indulging the weak and ſcrupulous with ſome favour and liberty to forbear thoſe things they ſcruple;) of becoming all things to all men to gain ſome, and pleaſing our Brother for his good to edification; and that all things be done in Charity, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> theſe call for ſome Conceſſions; as my Lord <hi>Hales</hi> in his <hi>Diſcourſe of Religion,</hi> tells us: Some allowance is to be made in the caſe or a weak Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, who on that account refuſeth, and cannot, though he would, obey. Either all the Commands of bearing with the infirmities of the weak, ſignifie thus much, (ſaith he) or nothing at all. And though the common Anſwer is, Is it not fitter that he ſhould ſubmit to the Church then the Church ſubmit to him? Yet that Anſwer, I preſume, is not ſufficient in this caſe; though there be a Duty that the Child owes to the Father, yet that will not excuſe the Father from the Duty which he owes to his Child, eſpecially when it is from a Conſcientious account that he refuſeth to obey.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Mr.</hi> Tulli<hi>'s Sermon of Moderation,</hi> p. 22. St. <hi>Paul</hi> made, himſelf all things to all men, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And how was he all things to all,<note place="margin">Biſhop <hi>Hall.</hi>
               </note> as a Learned Prelate of our own, asks the Queſtion, if he did not ſometime remit of his right to ſome.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:100559:14"/>
               <hi>Biſhop</hi> Saunderſon <hi>ad Aulam,</hi> Serm. 8. Sect. 38. We deal not like Chriſtians, no, nor like reaſonable Creatures, if we expect, all men ſhould come to our bent in every thing, and we our ſelves relent not our own ſtiffneſs in the leaſt matter for their ſakes. And even <hi>Dr.</hi> Sherlock <hi>of Religious Aſſemblies,</hi> p. 22. Speaks of making all reaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able condeſcenſions to the weakneſs or ignorance of ſome doubting and ſcrupulous Conſciences; and of giving eaſe to them, and relaxing the terms of Communion.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. But the experience of many years ſhews that our Brethren re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main unſatisfied in their Conſciences.</item>
               <item>2. They offer to give it in upon their Oaths, that they are not ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied in Conſcience, (as ſome to my knowledge would); and Dr. <hi>More</hi> tells us ſo on their behalf, I think in his <hi>Myſtery of Iniquity, and Anſwer touching Liberty in Religion,</hi> a place cited by a Noncon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formiſt in our Diſcourſe together.</item>
               <item>3. They ſeem to be in earneſt that it is really ſcruple and diſſatisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction in Conſcience, when they would part with their Benefices and People moſt dear unto them, and ſuffer Fines and Impriſonments ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then Conform.</item>
               <item>4. Again, Their Lives prove the ſame. Men whoſe Lives are all of a piece and uniform; ſuch as make Conſcience to keep from other ſins; why ſhould they not be believed in this wherein they plead Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience? Can their Integrity be diſproved that they are men of no Conſcience in other things. But I do verily believe our Nonconform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Brethren, eſpecially the moderate men of the Presbyterian Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion (not diſowning Epiſcopacy) to be of as unblameable Lives, as any ſort of men among us: And theſe are the men that we plead for to be taken into our Church again.</item>
            </list>
            <p>I ſhall cite ſome Conformiſts in Teſtimony of their Weakneſs and not Wilfulneſs in their Diſſent from us, and pleading for favour to the Weak.</p>
            <p>Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> as Sir <hi>Francis Walſingham</hi> tells us in his Letter to Monſieur <hi>Critoy</hi> of <hi>France,</hi> made a differeence between the Papiſts
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:100559:15"/>and Puritans in <hi>Conſcience,</hi> and Papiſts and Puritans of Faction and Sedition.</p>
            <p>It was not ſo judged by our Governours in that Age, when the <hi>Act of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niformity</hi> was firſt Eſtabliſhed; as if all Separatiſts muſt ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parate from wilfulneſs and obſtinacy; but a more Charitable interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation there was of mens ſcrupling Obedience [in Conformity]; as is evident by the relief given to ſuch by Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> who with the Advice of her Council put forth a Book of Articles to be Enqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red of at their Viſitation, and Preſentation to be made accordingly: And of Fifty Six in number there was not among them One that was judged offenſive on purpoſe, againſt the Rites and Ceremonies then Eſtabliſhed, which ſhewed they were not all <hi>wilful</hi> and <hi>obſtinate</hi> that could not Conform: And ſome Biſhops formed the <hi>Articles of En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiry,</hi> with more moderation. <hi>Nyes Suprem.</hi> p 40.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>In the Reaſons given in the Common-Prayer for Kneeling at the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion.</hi> Leaſt the ſame Kneeling ſhould by any perſons out of Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance and Infirmity [<hi>i. e.</hi> through Weakneſs] or out of Malice and Obſtinacy, be miſconſtrued and depraved, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Biſhop</hi> Jewels <hi>Anſwer</hi> to <hi>Mr.</hi> Hardings <hi>Preface in his Reply.</hi> Some of theſe that now be about you, being I truſt, not frowardly carried away with wilful Malice, but having the fear of God and reverent Zeal to do the beſt; though perhaps not knowledge ſufficient to judge what is beſt Was his Charity ſuch towards Papiſts? No doubt but it was as great to Diſſenting Proteſtants.</p>
            <p>Lloyds <hi>Stare Worthies, in the Life of Sir</hi> William Cecil, <hi>Lord</hi> Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leigh, <hi>in his Letter to Archbiſhop</hi> Whitgift, <hi>for ſome ſcruplous Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters:</hi> My Lord, I fear no ſenſual or wilful Recuſant [among thoſe he pleaded for]. I ſharply admoniſhed them, that if they will be di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſturbers in their Churches, they muſt be corrected. After follows the Lord <hi>Burleighs</hi> Character: He was not rigid; he would help the good natured, yet puniſh the ſtubborn; which ſhews thoſe were not ſuch (at leaſt not in his judgment) for whom he interceded.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>King</hi> Charles II. <hi>Declaration,</hi> Dec. 26. 1662. His Majeſty being therefore perſwaded that multitudes have ſuffered, being enſnared in their Conſciences, and not from wilfulneſs.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:100559:15"/>
               <hi>True State of the Primitive Church;</hi> Truly I think him very defe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive in Charity, however he abounds in Faith, who thinks all Papiſts, or Lutherans, or Calviniſts malitiouſly or wilfully blind.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Dr.</hi> Barrow <hi>on</hi> Eph 5.2. <hi>towards the end;</hi> if Chriſt and his Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, if the Service and Salvation of his People be our end; if we mind the ſame common Salvation, as the Apoſtle calleth it, the diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences which after remain amongſt us, ariſe purely from a narrow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and defect of Judgment, and not from any other root of Malig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nancy, or Hoſtility.</p>
            <p>How ſuch are to be dealt with we are told alſo, and what ſavour is to be ſhown them in reſpect of that their weakneſs, King <hi>Charles</hi> the Firſt's <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. Upon His Majeſties Retirement from <hi>Weſtminſter, Sect.</hi> 10. Sure that Man cannot be blamable to God or Man, who ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly endeavours to ſee the beſt reaſon of things, and faithfully fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows what he takes for reaſon; the uprightneſs of his intentions will excuſe the poſſible failings of his Underſtanding.</p>
            <p>Lord <hi>Faulkland</hi>'s Speech to the Houſe of Commons, 1641. If it be feared, that they will employ ſome of our Laws with a ſeverity beyond their intention, againſt ſome of their weaker Brethren, that we may be ſure to take away that Power, let us take away thoſe Laws.</p>
            <p>Dr. <hi>Puller</hi>'s Moderation of the Church of <hi>England, p.</hi> 26. Benig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity [<hi>i. e.</hi> favour] is to be ſhewed to the humble and peaceable, but it can in no wiſe be challenged by the proud and froward. <hi>Item. p.</hi> 24. The Execution of the Eccleſiaſtical Laws remitted only in conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the weakneſs of the People. <hi>Item p.</hi> 35. According to Equity (which is uſing as we ſay a Couſcience, <hi>p.</hi> 18.) Our Church deſires all her Laws may be interpreted. <hi>Benignius Leges Angliae ſunt inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretandae, quo voluntas earum conſervetur. Capienda eſt occaſio quae<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> praebet benignius reſponſum.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Biſhop</hi> Saunderſon <hi>on</hi> Rom. 14.3. Sect. 25. We are bound not to deſpiſe our Nonconforming Brethren, ſo far forth, as may probably appear to us, they are weak, and not wilful; and <hi>declares there are ſome ſuch,</hi> Sect. 29.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:100559:16"/>
               <hi>Doctor</hi> Barrow <hi>on</hi> Eph. 5.2. <hi>towards the end:</hi> As we deal with Children, allowing to the infirmities of their Age, their Ignorance, Frowardneſs, and Untoward Humour, without diſtracting them, ſo ſhould we with our Brethren, who labour under any weakneſs of Mind or Humour.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Doctor</hi> Tillotſon's <hi>Second Volume of Sermons,</hi> p. 195. It's great Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity to conſider the inveterate prejudices of Men, eſpecially which are rooted in Education, and which Men are confirmed in by the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verence they bear to thoſe that have been their Teachers; and great Allowances are to be given Men in this caſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Biſhop</hi> Tailor's <hi>Rules to his Clergy:</hi> Think no Man conſiderable upon the pretence of a tender Conſcience, unleſs he live a good Life; but if he be an humble Perſon, Modeſt, apt to Learn, and deſirous of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation, if he ſeeks for it in all wayes reaſonable and pious, and is obedient to Laws, then take care of him, uſe him tenderly, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade him meekly, reprove him gently, and deal mercifully with him, till <hi>God ſhall reveal that alſo unto him,</hi> in which his unavoidable trouble and temptation lies.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Principles and Practices,</hi> &amp;c. p. 333. They (<hi>i. e.</hi> the Moderate Men of the Church of <hi>England</hi>) Believe that thoſe who differ from the Eſtabliſhed way of Religion, ought not to be eſteem'd, or dealt with, as Men of tender Conſciences, [<hi>i. e.</hi> weak ones] who are not quiet, and peaceable, modeſt and charitable in their behaviour towards others, that are not of their way and mind, but muſt needs be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fronting of Authority.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Judge</hi> Hale<hi>'s Diſcourſe of Religion,</hi> p. 21. Some perchance tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported too far in ſcrupling or oppoſing ſome Ceremonies or Forms, not from frowardneſs, and peeviſhneſs, or a Spirit of oppoſition, but in the ſincerity and ſimplicity of their hearts; thoſe though miſtaken, yet certainly deſerve Compaſſion, Tenderneſs, yea, and Love alſo, much rather than ſeverity and contempt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Doctor</hi> Haſcard, <hi>Dean of</hi> Windſor <hi>on</hi> Eph. 4.23. To allow no Grace for Common Errours and Frailties; this is ſeverity and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mercifulneſs.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:100559:16"/>
               <hi>Doctor</hi> Good<hi>'s F<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>mianus and Dubit.</hi> p. 164. Thoſe to be among them that are of a quiet and, peaceable Spirit, agreeing with us in the moſt neceſſary points of Religion. He gives us Reaſons, why Debauchery and Profaneneſs ought to be more ſeverely puniſhed, that Negative Separation, and Simple Nonconformity. <hi>[His Second Reaſon.]</hi> The Sins of Prophaneneſs and Debauchery being wilful (for Drunkards and profane Perſons do not plead Ignorance and Weakneſs,) are of a more malignant Nature than ſins of Ignorance, though ſuch as was not altogether invincible.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Doctor</hi> Burnet, <hi>the Biſhop of</hi> Salisbury<hi>'s Exhortation to Peace and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion,</hi> p. 34. Let <hi>us alſo conſider one another,</hi> as Brethren, let us bear with one anothers infirmities, let us give ſome allowances to the weakneſs of thoſe that are miſlead by the force of Education, and the byas of Vulgar prejudices.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Serious and Compaſſionate Enquiry,</hi> p. 204. He that pleads for Compaſſion upon the account of his weakneſs, muſt firſt willingly ſubmit himſelf to Inſtruction. Secondly, Be uniformly Conſcientiious. Thirdly, He will do all that he can, if he cannot do all that is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded. Fourthly, He may forbear judging and cenſuring them that do all that the Law commands. Fifthly, Will freely part with Money and Worldly Matters to preſerve his own Innocency and Peace. Again, If after all my Endeavours of ſatisfying my ſelf to obey the Humane Law, the thing commanded ſeem unlawful; I ſay this caſe is pityable. Diſobedience then will be only a Sin of Infirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, which is pityable among Men upon conſideration of common Humanity, and is pardonable with God, as other Errors are on a general Repentance.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Mr.</hi> Dodwel<hi>'s Letters about Holy Orders;</hi> When you have reduced them [i. e. <hi>the Miniſter, the Perſons in his Pariſh</hi>] to this Excellent Temper (as <hi>p.</hi> 19.) to practiſe the common Duties of Chriſtianity, if you could not perſwade them to aſſent to what you ſay through the weakneſs of their underſtandings, or your unskilfulneſs to plead for a good Cauſe, (<hi>i. e.</hi> Conformity) with Advantage, you muſt needs conclude them invincibly Ignorant, and therefore Excuſable before God in this regard, as well as poſitively acceptable in others; and therefore muſt be as Charitable in your Judgment, as you believe God will prove favourable in his Final Sentence.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:100559:17"/>
               <hi>Mr.</hi> Smithies <hi>Spirit of Meekneſs,</hi> p. 68. As the <hi>Galathians</hi> were <hi>overtaken in a fault.</hi> Gal 6.1. So we muſt account them likewiſe, who have diſſented from us. When Men are guilty of Errors of Practice, they are wilful and obſtinate, for they know they are wrong, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> But no Man runs wilfully into an Error of Judgment, but it's through the weakneſs of Judgment, and inſtability of mind, for which he is to be pitied; <hi>Idem p.</hi> 70. I mention theſe inſtances, becauſe ſome Men will not be perſwaded, that there is any thing but wilfulneſs, and obſtinacy, that is the cauſe of Mens Diſſenting, and therefore they ought not to be treated with the <hi>Spirit of Meekneſs,</hi> p. 71. If we conſider what Education many have had, we may well conclude that they were overtaken in the fault of Separation, not that it was a wilful choice.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Mr.</hi> Kettlewel<hi>'s Meaſure of Chriſtian Obedience,</hi> Edit. 2. p. 494. Some prejudices get into Mens Minds, not through any thing of an evil and diſobedient Heart, but only through weakneſs of the Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding; they are not of an underſtanding ſufficient to examine things exactly, when they embrace their prejudice; for their reaſon is dim and ſhort ſighted, weak and unexperienced, unable throughly to ſearch into the Nature of things, and to judge of the various weight, and juſt force of Reaſons, to ſift and ranſack, ſeparate and diſtinguiſh between Solidity and Shew, Truth and Falſhood: <hi>p.</hi> 496 <hi>Idem p.</hi> 117. Love to others produces in us, if they have honeſt Hearts, but yet are weak in Judgment and Knowledge, a Compaſſionate ſence of their weakneſs, and endeavours to relieve them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Argument for Tol and Indulg. in difference not of Faith, but of Opinions,</hi> Print. 81. It pleaſing God in Infinite Goodneſs to reſpect the Will, the Intention, the ſincere Endeavour of his Servants, and for the reſt to put upon Humane Weakneſs and Infirmity, that Weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and Infirmity, which he will pardon; and if God himſelf have ſo much Tenderneſs and Compaſſion for Humane Weakneſs and Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfection, ſhall Men themſelves have none for one another? <hi>p.</hi> 5. <hi>Item</hi> 13. And certainly it would much import to healing our brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, and to lay the Heats and Animoſities that Reign among us, if we more regarded the Conſcience, they who do diſſent from us, do make, and the good Deſigns and Ends they aim at, than the very Opinions and Practices themſelves, in which they diſſent: For in the
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:100559:17"/>former all good Chriſtians agree, and in the latter will ever differ, We ought highly to honour Tenderneſs of Conſcience, and Intenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons directed to the Glory of God, and the Common Good of the Church, and of the World, wherever we find them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Mr.</hi> Hoffman<hi>'s Conſider. of preſent uſe, on</hi> Rom. 15.6, 7. <hi>That the ſtrong ought to bear with the weak,</hi> &amp;c. p. 18. By the weak, I mean thoſe which are really ſo, and not ſuch as uſe it for an obſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate and ungovernable pretence: When we hear a Man ſincerely from the bottom of his Heart, ſaying, That he cannot think that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different which others do; that he cannot admit things that are really lawful in others Opinions, to appear ſo in his. A Man that is ſtrong ought to pity ſuch a ones weakneſs, <hi>Item. p.</hi> 21. They ſeem to be in earneſt, when their blindneſs will inable them to part with that which is dear to them, rather than obey.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Mr.</hi> Allen, <hi>late</hi> of Henfield <hi>in</hi> Suſſex, <hi>Pref. to his Sermon,</hi> We de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire the trouble of none that are peaceable.</p>
            <p>Thus you have ſeen how the Conformiſts plead for favour to them in the general; and ſure it might be as uſeful and beneficial to the Church in this particular (Condeſcention to their weakneſs) as any other.</p>
            <p>Beſides all this, I could ſhow out of the Works of Eminent Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formiſts, that it is acknowledged by them, that there are Good and Worthy Men among the Diſſenters from the Church of <hi>England.</hi> And why ſhould not ſome conſideration be had of them, and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what to be done for their ſakes, who are prized by Conformiſts as Men of Worth and Goodneſs. And ſurely, it will be no loſs to our Church to loſe a few things that may be ſpared well enough, if She ſhall gain her Brethren by that means; eſpecially when the loſs is of ſuch things as have need of an Alteration or Abrogation for the common good of Proteſtants. And I hope, ſaith Mr. <hi>Claud</hi> to the Biſhop of <hi>London,</hi> you will not be wanting in the Duties of Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, and the Spirit of Peace; and that when the Diſpute ſhall be only of ſome Temperaments, or of ſome Ceremonies that are a ſtumbling-block, and which in themſelves are nothing in compariſon with an intire re-union, you will make it ſeen, that you love the Spouſe
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:100559:18"/>of your Maſter more than your ſelves. This indeed would manifeſt in the Fathers of the Church a true Fatherly Affection, great Humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity and Condeſcention, if they ſhall at length yield ſomewhat to the Infirmity and Importunity of Proteſtant Brethren. And it is highly probable, that ſuch Conceſſions and Alterations, as to take in our Diſſenting Brethren, would take away moſt of thoſe Evils that have troubled the Church. It were the beſt way and means to put a ſtop to the Courſe of Separation. For when the moſt eminent and conſiderable Men of the Nonconformiſts were taken in (as certainly they would come in) the reſt would be diſcouraged and diſcounte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nanced in their Separation, and we might hope that they would fall off by degrees, and in time be wholly recovered to the Church again. Hereby a great many Miniſters conſiderable for Gifts and Grace, might do ſervice in the Church, who muſt otherwiſe be ſilent, or exerciſe their Miniſtry in a way of Separation. As the Separation will ceaſe much by a Comprehenſion, ſo will the Envy, Hatred, Malice, and Uncharitableneſs that accompanies a divided Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate ceaſe in the ſame meaſure. And it is to be hoped this would ſtrengthen the hands of Diſcipline, and turn the Cenſures of the Church and their force againſt the ſcandalous open Evil-livers, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of vexing of Diſſenters. And perhaps in order to this Accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modation, it might be deſirable to conſider of the Nonconformiſts Motion, <hi>page</hi> 61. We confeſs that ſome Forms have their laudible uſe to cure that Errour and Vice, that lieth on the other ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tream: And might we but ſomtimes have the liberty to interpoſe ſuch words, as are needful to call home, and quicken Attention and Affection, we ſhould think that a convenient Conjunction of both might be a well-tempered means to the Common Conſtitutions of moſt. By a mixt Worſhip, partly by a Form; and in ſome part (be it but little) otherwiſe, not as of neceſſity for all, but allowance to ſome who may be habitually apt for it, as Miniſters will increaſe their Gifts, attaining more Holy Skill, and Wiſdom, and Ability in Prayer by this means, and be more fitted and ready for Ejaculatory Prayer, and other ſort of Occaſional Prayer after the Examination of their Hearts and Lives, whether dayly, or upon ſet times of Faſting and Humiliation; or to follow the Word (read or Preached) with Prayer for a Bleſſing on that, and the Sacraments, which with all the Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances of God are Sanctified, or Bleſſed by Prayer. Miniſters beſides by this means being more frequent in the performance of this ſo great
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:100559:18"/>and neceſſary a Duty, will be more ready and inclinable to it at all times, with much eaſe and freedom, ſweetneſs and delight, which Naturally, much more Spiritually proceed from Uſe and Cuſtom. And the People will be encouraged by the Examples of their Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters to do the like, and follow them. And this would mightily pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote Religion, all our Religion being like to riſe or fall, as we riſe or fall in this Duty.</p>
            <p n="7">7. To continue our <hi>Common Prayer</hi> in all and every thing the ſame, it is to be feared will continue, if not perpetuate Schiſm. While the things ſcrupled and excepted againſt continue, we have little or no hopes of gaining our Brethren. They are never like to be ſo well ſatisfied in Conſcience as to the Aſſent and Conſent to all and every thing, and the undoubted certainty of Baptized Infants Salvation (which Biſhop <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſher</hi> in his Body of Divinity, of Baptiſm doubted of, and ſo do ſome Conformiſts now, Curates, and others, who can uſe the Baptiſmal Office) and as to the Sign of the Croſs, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> as to come up to a full Conformity to the preſent eſtabliſhed Worſhip. There are but four means of curing Schiſme, either by Inſtruction or Toleration, Reprehenſion, or Comprehenſion. They have had Inſtruction long enough; one Conformiſt after another writing for Conformity, ſome in the Spirit of Meekneſs, ſome with another man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of Spirit; and ſtill they have been anſwered, and the Nonconfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſts remained unconvinced, unſatisfied. And as to Toleration of their different Aſſemblies, there were no cure of Schiſm that way; though I think, it is of the better ſort, like Mr. <hi>Greenham</hi>'s Anſwer to the Biſhop of <hi>Ely,</hi> who told him there was a Schiſm in the Church, and asked him where the fault lay? <q>On either ſide ſaid he, if they violated the Laws of Love, on neither part (as to culpable Schiſm) if they lived lovingly together, as they ſhould do notwithſtanding the difference of their Judgments.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Further, <hi>Miſchief of Separation,</hi> page 18. <q>Men may pleaſe themſelves in talking of preſerving Love and Peace under ſeparate Congregations; but our own ſad Experience ſhows the contrary. For as nothing tends more to unite Mens hearts, than joyning together in the ſame Prayers and Sacraments; ſo nothing doth more alienate Mens Affections, than withdrawing from each other into ſeparate Communions. Therefore as large a Compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſion as may be is deſirable;</q> and no more Toleration of other
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:100559:19"/>Worſhip than neceſſity requires, becauſe Toleration without a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſion will weaken any Eſtabliſhed Church. As to Reprehenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on (ſeverity I mean by that word) it may make Men Hypocrites, and drive many to Church, who will fall off again, as ſoon as the ſeverities ceaſe. Men are reaſonable Creatures, and what they do, it ſhould be a reaſonable ſervice, from an enlightened mind, and well-ſatisfied Conſcience, not by force and violence done to their Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences, diſſembling with God and the World. For neither is God ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved by ſuch, nor their Souls edified, nor the Communion of Saints encreaſed by ſuch an Hypocritical Union and Communion with our Church. And though it is not to be denied, but that ſome may, by ſuch ſeverities, be put upon a more Impartial ſearch and enquiry into the Tearmes of Communion with us, and ſo be ſatisfied really, yet theſe are but few, the far greater part forſaking us, when once the laſh is taken away, and they come to have their liberty. The laſt and the beſt means is Comprehenſion; and that muſt be by yielding ſomewhat for Peace ſake on either ſide. And ſurely, there is no ſuch wide breach, but that there might be a cloſing, an healing, if we would ſet our ſelves in good earneſt to it, and would not be too ſtiff and ſelf-willed. And to this end perhaps it were deſirable, that, as the <hi>Dutch</hi> did us the Honour of having ſome of our Divines at their Synod for compoſing differences among them; ſo that we might take in the Aſſiſtance of ſome of their Divines, either by their Perſonal Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, or Advice by Letter, as Mr. <hi>Le Moyne,</hi> and the <hi>others of France,</hi> Mr. <hi>De L' Angle,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Claud,</hi> worthy Perſons, made ſome Eſſay towards an Union in their Letters to his Lordſhip the <hi>Biſhop of London.</hi> This would add a greater Authority unto what ſhould be ſo eſtabliſhed. And the more Proteſtant Churches that aſſiſted therein, the better and more forcible bond of Union.</p>
            <p>But it will be objected (or hath been) nothing will ſatisfie; The Diſſenters will never come in.</p>
            <p>I Anſwer, At King <hi>Charles</hi> the <hi>Seconds</hi> Return, though they did de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire many Alterations in the Worſhip, as to Words and Sentences, Ceremonies, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Yet they drew up the principal matters in a ſhort Letter to the moſt Reverend Arch-Biſhop and Biſhops, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> mention'd p. 30, 31, 32. of the <hi>Grand Debate.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:100559:19"/>
2. It may juſtly be ſuppoſed, that among thoſe Objections and Exceptions againſt ſeveral things therein, (when his Majeſties Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion gave them that liberty to make ſuch Reaſonable and neceſſary Alterations, Corrections, and Amendments, as ſhould be agreed up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on at that Conference, to be needful and expedient,) there were ſome things, which were judged by them to be inconvenient, other things to be unlawful. If they had been put to it to declare, what they held to be ſinful and unlawful to be ſubmitted to, I doubt not but they would have cut off many things, as only inconvenient, and not ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarily or unavoidably evil, and ſo have been ſatisfied as to the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of Conformity with leſs.</p>
            <p>Another Anſwer. Judge <hi>Hales</hi> with the Lord Keeper <hi>Bridgeman,</hi> and Biſhop <hi>Wilkins</hi> drew up a Model of Abatements and Condeſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions for a Comprehenſion of the more moderate Diſſenters, and a li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mited Indulgence towards ſuch as could not be brought within the Comprehenſion; and when after ſeveral Conferences with two of the Eminenteſt Presbyterian Divines, heads were agreed on, and ſome abatements to be made, and ſome explanations were to be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted of, they put them into the form of a Bill to be Preſented to the next Seſſion of Parliament. <hi>In the Life of Sir</hi> Matthew Hale <hi>by Dr.</hi> Burnet <hi>Biſhop of</hi> Salisbury, <hi>p.</hi> 41, 42. He gives us the Reaſons that prevailed at that time againſt it, <hi>p.</hi> 70, 71, 72, 73. The Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cils and Reaſons againſt it being more acceptable to ſome concealed Papiſts then in power, as has ſince appeared too evidently, the whole project for Comprehenſion was let fall; and thoſe who had ſet it a foot, came to be looked on with an evil eye, as ſecret favourers of Diſſenters, underminers of the Church, and every thing elſe that jealouſie and diſtaſte could caſt on them.</p>
            <p>A fourth Anſwer ſhall be given you out of the <hi>Conformiſts Plea for the Nonconformiſts,</hi> Part 4. p. 26, 27. In Anſwer to that Objection, ſhould we yield to any one of theſe we are far from gaining the reſt.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. Gain any of them, and we ſhall be the more and ſtronger by that addition.</item>
               <item>2. Except the Presbyterians, the moſt of the other Diſſenters agree in their Modes of Government: So that what you grant to one Party, is granted to more.</item>
               <item>
                  <pb n="32" facs="tcp:100559:20"/>
3. Is it Reaſon and Charity, that thoſe who would unite ſhall not, becauſe all will not upon ſome abatements.</item>
               <item>4. Gain ſome, and they will help to draw in others.</item>
               <item>5. The more are United, the fewer remain to be Tolerated; by which Toleration I mean no more, but a forbearing one another in Love, with the uſe of Goſpel means to convince and gain them, if poſſible, and by the Civil Sword to reſtrain and ſuppreſs them, when it ſhall be neceſſary, and dangerous to the State, and not before. Thus that Excellent Perſon has given a moſt ſolid Anſwer, with a moſt Chriſtian Spirit: I ſhall add what I had from one of his Majeſties Chaplains by way of Anſwer to the ſame Objection: If there be but room or way made for them the fault will be their own if they will not come in. If the Mother will receive her Children, and enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertain them as her own in love, they muſt bear the blame if they will not return home. I might add that they will ſhew themſelves unworthy of that favour given them in the <hi>Act of Toleration,</hi> if they grow more obſtinate and averſe, and utter enemies to an accommo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation, and may provoke Authority to take it away.</item>
            </list>
            <p>Another Objection, <hi>Why ſhould there be any Conceſſions or Altera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, when the preſent terms of Conformity are Lawful?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>I Anſwer,</hi> They may be unlawful to them, (for to him that eſteem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth any thing to be unlawful, to him it is unlawful; according to that, <hi>Rom.</hi> 14.14.) but not <hi>ex natura rerum, per ſe,</hi> and ſo they may be Lawful to us, and our Conſciences; or may be Lawful to one and not another, in point of Practice and Conformity; ſo that yield<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to their Conſciences and their Scruples may conſiſt with the up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rightneſs and integrity of our own, and a Conformity upon juſt grounds of conviction and ſatisfaction.</p>
            <p>A ſecond Anſwer: The yielding to the Diſſenters may be ſuch, as not utterly to take away any thing, but to leave ſome things at liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, as the Ceremonies; eſpecially the Sign of the Croſs. And as the great Dean of St. <hi>Pauls</hi> motioned, whether thoſe expreſſions, which ſuppoſe the ſtrict exerciſe of Diſcipline in <hi>Burying the Dead,</hi> were not better left at liberty in our preſent caſe; [there being a confeſſed
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:100559:20"/>want and neglect of Diſcipline]: And whether requiring only an uſe of the Liturgy, and approbation of that uſe, and ſubſcription to it, leaving the ſubſcription according to the Canon, and the Aſſent and Conſent, to all and every thing contained and preſcribed, according as perſons Conſciences are ſatisfied or unſatisfied therein: It is certain that the Uniformity in Worſhip, and the end of that <hi>Act for <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nifor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity</hi> is anſwered by an uſe of the Prayers, as by Law Eſtabliſhed. No doubt but many would Conform upon ſuch a Liberty granted, who cannot ſatisfie their Conſciences in the preſent terms of Confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity: But the leaving things thus at Liberty, were no Argument that they are Unlawful.</p>
            <p>Further; Such yielding as this would make no ſuch Alteration but that our preſent Common-Prayer Books would ſerve; which they might do, if ſeveral Repetitions were left out, as of the Lords Prayer, which we uſed ſo often at firſt, (and continued ſince becauſe received at firſt,) that the people might learn it in their <hi>Engliſh</hi> Tongue; even thoſe many that could not read, and uſed before to ſay it in Latin, <hi>Pater noſter,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Other Repetitions, as of the <hi>Gloria Patri</hi> after every Pſalm, (yielded to be left out by thoſe who met at the Biſhop of <hi>Lincolns</hi> Houſe, in King <hi>Charles</hi> I. time) and the one of the Creeds, uſing the <hi>Nicene</hi> Creed upon ſome certain days only: Which were the better way of leſſening the length of the Prayers, by taking away ſome Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petitions, which our Diſſenting Brethren do not pretend to be unlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, but only to be inconvenient, as ſome Conformiſts acknowledge alſo.</p>
            <p>Third Anſwer: Further, <hi>The Preface to the Common-Prayer</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged, <q>that the particular Forms of Worſhip, and the Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies appointed to be uſed, being things in their own nature indifferent and alterable; it is but reaſonable, ſuch changes and alterations ſhould be made therein, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>It ſaith further, <q>That in the Reigns of ſeveral Princes of Bleſſed Memory ſince the Reformation, the Church upon juſt and weigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Conſiderations hath yielded to make ſuch Alterations, as in their reſpective times were thought convenient.</q> But when the
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:100559:21"/>Church did yield in thoſe matters, ſhe did not yield them up as utter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly unlawful, but inconvenient, or leſs ſuitable to thoſe times; <hi>&amp; pro conditione temporum.</hi> ſome things are more, ſome leſs convenient, and fit for continuance or alteration accordingly.</p>
            <p>Fourth Anſwer: The preſent terms of Conformity will be the ſame as to their Lawfulneſs or Unlawfulneſs, whether there be any condeſcenſions for Diſſenters, or none at all. As I am a Conformiſt both in judgment and practice, ſo I could offer Arguments in defence of my preſent Conformity, as well as for Conceſſions to the Noncon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formiſts. Yet the Learned Biſhop <hi>Coſins</hi> declared in his laſt Teſtament, that it was the great duty of us all to Unite, and I am ſure it is ſo, and that it is no duty of any at all, to cenſure or condemn the preſent terms of Conformity as Unlawful, upon the account of any conceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons or receſſions from them, for ſo good an end as an happy Re-union and Comprehenſion. I need not remind you in how many Precepts this Duty is enjoyned, how tenderly and compaſſionately the Apoſtles of our Lord dealt with weak ones, how earneſtly they changed us to receive them, to bear with them, to become all things to them to gain the weak, to pleaſe them to their edification, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Arguments enough to convince us that it is our duty, whatever the World ſay, or think of us, to yield ſomewhat to the weakneſs of our Brethren, and to relax, as the Author of the <hi>Serious and Compaſſionate Enquiry</hi> has it, <hi>p.</hi> 102. Making the terms of Communion more free and eaſie; this is highly recommended by ſome good men, as the moſt proper expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient for a Proteſtant Church in our condition.</p>
            <p>Another Objection. <hi>It would be a diſhonour (ſay ſome) to our firſt Reformers, to take away thoſe things which they Eſtabliſhed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To which I Anſwer; as <hi>True ſtate of the Primitive Church.</hi> The Fathers of this Church, when they Reformed this Nation from Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery, were deſirous to fetch off as many as they could, retaining for this cauſe all the Ceremonies, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Certainly we cannot do our Fore-Fathers a greater <hi>honour,</hi> than to obſerve their Rule of Reaſon, to conform to the times; and therefore they are groſly miſtaken, who think it a diſhonour to them, for us to take away what they have Eſtabliſhed, when we keep cloſe to the reaſon wherefore they did Eſtabliſh it.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:100559:21"/>
               <hi>Iren.</hi> p. 225. This Temper was uſed by our Reformers, in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing our Liturgy in reference to the Papiſts, to whom they had then an eſpecial eye, as being the only party then appearing whom they deſired to draw into their Communion, by coming as near them, as they well and ſafely could; I ſay the ſame reaſon which at that time made them yield ſo far to them, would now have perſwaded them to alter and lay aſide thoſe things which yield matter of offence to any of the ſame perſwaſion with themſelves. For ſurely none will be ſo uncharitable towards thoſe of his own Profeſſion, as to think there is not as much reaſon to yield in compliance with them as with the Papiſts. Further, Lloyds <hi>State Worthies</hi> in <hi>Quarto,</hi> p. 998. in the Life of Archbiſhop <hi>Laud,</hi> he brings in that Biſhop, diſliking Mr. <hi>Calvins</hi> words of Cenſure, <hi>Tolerabiles ineptias,</hi> who knew not ſaid the Biſhop the temper of the Nation, requiring then not what was abſolutely beſt, but moſt conveniently good. And thus our Reformers did what was beſt in their days, or moſt conveniently good: Even as <hi>Ariſtotles</hi> Organon might be beſt in the days of old, but now the caſe is altered, and the reading Lectures out of that Book is commonly with leſs profit, than other Logicks would be; the caſe may be applicable to ſome things at leaſt in the Common-Prayers, if not the Worſhip it ſelf, as not done ſo much to edifying, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And the Reformers reaſon for their Impoſition ceaſeth, which was the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>largement of the Church, by gaining and winning as many as could be, to our Communion: The Papiſts came to this Worſhip till the 10th or 12th year of Queen <hi>Elizabeths</hi> Reign: But now it hinders and ſhuts ſome of our Reformed Proteſtant Brethren out of our Church; and ſo the reaſon which made at firſt for the impoſition, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth as much now for the abrogation of ſome things therein.</p>
            <p>I ſay again, not a diſhonour to our firſt Reformers; becauſe a due acknowledgment may be made of their worth, and the work of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation in their days, that it was the beſt, the fitteſt, or at leaſt praiſe-worthy. Our Forefathers, who knew what Popery and a Maſs book was by ſad Experience, rejoyced, that they had Prayers ſound for the ſubſtance, and purged from the Corruptions of the Maſs book, and looked upon it as a wonderful Bleſſing from Heaven, and were thankful. And if ſomewhat be inconvenient, and leſs ſuitable to the genius of the people in theſe days, not ſinful and unlawful, or unmeet for good Chriſtians to joyn in; I preſume no diſhonour will
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:100559:22"/>be done to our firſt Reformers; who, as ſeveral are apt to imagine, if they had lived in theſe days, would have taken at leaſt ſome few things away for the enlargement of our Communion.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, Gods Honour is greater than that of our firſt Reformers; but God is highly diſhonoured by this Worſhip, as it is at preſent performed, careleſly, negligently, under contempt by many, and by moſt, I am afraid, little regarded, as to the devout uſe of it. And the Queſtion muſt end in this; whether God will be more Honoured by the continuance of the Common Prayers, as at preſent; or whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther (with Submiſſion to the Wiſdom of our Governours) it may not admit of an alteration in ſome things for the better? Whether it is like to do moſt good to Souls, and beſt attain the ends of Worſhip, in its preſent uſe, or any Amendments or Conceſſions for a Compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſion: So be it, Gods Worſhip be done to edifying by the greater part of our Congregations, in the City and Country both, God will have the Glory, and all good Chriſtians will be ſatisfied.</p>
            <p>Another Objection. <hi>What need of a Comprehenſion? Are we not as well without it? What ſhall we be the better for it?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To which I Anſwer; There are no doubt a Thouſand Bleſſings of Heaven and Earth accompanying that Church ſtate, which like the Heavenly Society is at Unity in it ſelf. If there were any Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity here upon Earth that enjoyed a perfection of Love and Peace, how ambitious would Mortals be to enter into that Peaceful Society. But the neareſt approach that we can make unto it is by a <hi>Philadel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phian</hi> ſtate. An Heavenly thing is Unity, as <hi>Nazianzen</hi> well ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved, <hi>Pugnas &amp; diſſidia neſrcire Deum &amp; Angelos;</hi> No broyls, no jars in Heaven, nothing but Peace there, and it is a kind of Heaven upon Earth, when Brethren dwell together in Unity, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 133.1. <hi>Behold how good and pleaſant a thing it is,</hi> &amp;c. Pleaſant to behold, a lovely ſight to ſee an Army marching in an exact order; and as amia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and acceptable to hear people of the ſame Pariſh, Town, City, and Kingdom pouring out their joint requeſts, with one Mouth, and one Heart praying for the Peace and Proſperity of <hi>Zion.</hi> O the Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefits of Union are unſpeakably great! I profeſs my ſelf to ſtand ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miring the vanity of this contentious World that values ſuch a ſtate
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:100559:22"/>no more. Hear what men of the moſt ſerene temper, men that aſpired after it, if it were poſſible to attain to ſome good degree of it, or ſomewhat like it, by living Peaceably with all men, and by being Peacemakers.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Benefits of Peace and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>LOrd</hi> Bacons <hi>Eſſays,</hi> p. 13. <hi>Speaking of Peace in the Church:</hi> It containeth infinite Bleſſings, it eſtabliſheth Faith, it kindleth Charity, and it turneth the Labours of Writing and Reading of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſies, into Treatiſes of Mortification and Devotion.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Biſhop</hi> Andrews <hi>Sermons,</hi> p. 672. The Spirit dwells not but where Unity and Love is. — Think of this ſeriouſly, and ſet it down, that <hi>at</hi> Salem <hi>is his Tabernacle;</hi> and <hi>Salem</hi> is Peace; and ſo the Fathers read it, <hi>in pace factus eſt locus ejus,</hi> make that place for him, and he will ſay, here is my Reſt, here will I dwell, for I have a delight therein.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Mr.</hi> Vertues <hi>Plea for Peace.</hi> Chriſt hath ſaid, <hi>Bleſſed are the Peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>makers, they ſhall be called the Children of God.</hi> Matth. 5.9. As we would ſhare in this Bleſſedneſs, let it be our ſtudy. <hi>Item,</hi> p. 51. Would we ſee good, and enjoy long days, would we be ſure that we have that Wiſdom which is from above, be peaceable, wrangle not for trifles, contend not about uncertainties.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Dr.</hi> Goods <hi>Firmianus &amp; Dubit antius,</hi> p 165. It is not to be doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, but that Peace and Unity, and Love among our ſelves, would much diſhearten thoſe reſtleſs enemies of our Church and State, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and cauſe Religion and Primitive Chriſtianity to flouriſh in our miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable divided Nation; while that time, which is now ſpent in vain Wranglings and unchriſtian Contentions, would be better employed
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:100559:23"/>in devout Prayer, Holy Meditation, and Mortification of our Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptions, in Duties of Piety towards Almighty God, and of Love, Mercy and Charity one towards another.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Mr.</hi> Jekyls <hi>Sermons on</hi> Jer. 5.29. <hi>p.</hi> 30. Next to Peace with God, without which all other ſecurity will prove deceitful, Unity amongſt our ſelves is certainly the moſt effectual thing to the making of us an happy people; and till that be attained, we may poſſibly be quiet, but we ſhall never be ſafe.</p>
               <p>I ſhall conclude this with an excellent Speech of that Pious and Peaceable Prelate, Dr. <hi>Reynolds,</hi> in his Sermon of <hi>Self-denyal,</hi> to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the end; It were worth not only our Faſting and Prayer; but our Studying, our Sweating, our Bleeding, our Dying, to recover Peace to the Church, and Unity amongſt Brethren again.</p>
               <p>I could argue alſo from the miſchievous effects and conſequences of our Diviſions, that the caſe of our Church muſt be very ſad and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plorable while our Diviſions and Confuſions in matters of Religion continue. <hi>Malorum ilias,</hi> a multitude of evils throng in upon a Church through its unchriſtian Diviſions. A divided ſtate is an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happy ſtate; it is a ſtate of Separation from God as well as from their Brethren.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Biſhop</hi> Andrews <hi>Sermons,</hi> p. 672. And what is there would ſooner grieve him, (the Holy Spirit) and make him to quit us, than diſcord or diſunion? Among divided men or minds he will not dwell; not but where Unity and Love is. They may talk of the Spirit without theſe in vain. To ſay Truth, who would be hired to dwell in <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhecks, Pſal.</hi> 120.5. where nothing is but continual jars and jangles? Such places, ſuch men are even as <hi>Torida Zona,</hi> not habitable by the Spirit, by this Spirit: But for the Spirit of Diviſion, <hi>ut habitet inter eos Daemon,</hi> a fit place for the Devil to dwell among ſuch. And ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly he that hath an heart affected with any ſenſe of the miſerable caſe of our divided Church (though bleſſed be God not in ſo lamentable a caſe now as in former years) he that hath any concern for it muſt needs be convinced that we are not well, cannot be well in our mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiplicity of Diviſions.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="39" facs="tcp:100559:23"/>
                  <hi>The Lord Chancellor</hi> Hides <hi>Speech to the Parliament,</hi> 1660, He calls it a ſad Conſideration, that muſt make every Religious Heart to bleed, to ſee Religion, which ſhould be the ſtrongeſt or Obligations, and cement of Affection, and Brotherly kindneſs and Compaſſion, made by the perverſe wranglings of paſſionate and froward Men, the Ground of all Animoſity, Hatred, Malice, and Revenge. My Lords and Gentlemen, ſaith he, this Diſquiſition hath coſt the King many a ſigh, many a ſad hour, when he hath conſidered the almoſt irrepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Reproach the Proteſtant Religion hath undergone from the Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions and Diſtractions, which have been ſo notorious in this Kingdom.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Biſhop</hi> Saunderſon<hi>'s Sermons,</hi> ad Aulam, Serm. 9. Sect. 30; Odious to God, and grievous to every Godly Man it is, when ſuch Voices as theſe are heard in the Church, I am of <hi>Paul,</hi> and I am of <hi>Cephas,</hi> and I of <hi>Apollo.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> in the Life of Sir <hi>Matthew Hale</hi> ſaith, that he much lamented that ſo many Miniſters were ſilenced, the Church weakned, Papiſts ſtrengthned, the cauſe of Love and Piety greatly wronged and hindred by the preſent differences about Conformity.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Doctor</hi> Good<hi>'s Firmianus &amp; Dubitantius,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>p.</hi> 152; 'Tis indeed much to be lamented that we ſhould quarrel about Mint and Cum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>min, to the prejudice of the more weighty and material duties, and ſcandal of our Religion.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Cauſes of the decay of Chriſtian Piety,</hi> p. 424. Amidſt all our impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunate pretences to Piety, if there be indeed any ſuch thing amongſt us, methinks, it ſhould give us ſome relentings, make us ſadly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider, what a deplorable Condition we have brought that very Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion into by our Diviſions.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Biſhop of</hi> Salisbury<hi>'s Exhortation to Peace and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity,</hi> p. 30. There have ariſen among us ſuch heats, ſo much bitterneſs, ſo violent an averſion to one another, that it muſt needs beget great Grief, and ſad Apprehenſions in all that look on, and judge impartially.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Principles and Practices of ſome Mod.</hi> &amp;c. p. 4. It pains me to the Heart when I conſider, to what a prodigious heighth about matters in
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:100559:24"/>Religion our feuds are grown, and how utterly averſe the too many Sects and Parties we are crumbled into, are, to entertain thoughts of Peace and Accommodation.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity of the Catholick Church,</hi> p. 1. Whoſoever with an Impar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial Eye, and a truly Religious concern for the Honour of God, the Credit of the Goſpel, and the Salvation of Men, looks into the State of Chriſtendom, he will ſcarce find any greater cauſe of ſorrowful Reflections, than from the many Diviſions and Animoſities which have diſtracted and ſeparated its Parts.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Mr.</hi> Wakes <hi>Serm. on</hi> Rom. 15.5, 6, 7. I do not believe there is any good Chriſtian ſo little affected with thoſe unhappy Diviſions, under which the Church at this day labours, as not both heartily to deplore them, and to think that nothing could be too much, that might innocently be done on all hands for the redreſſing of them. And to ſhow that theſe Worthy Men had cauſe to complain, and bewail our Diviſions, I ſhall Exemplifie the Evils.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="41" facs="tcp:100559:24"/>
               <head>The Miſchief of our Diviſions.</head>
               <p>THE Firſt Miſchief promoting Atheiſme. Arch-Biſhop <hi>Grindal</hi> in his <hi>Fair Warning,</hi> Part 2. Edit. 1663, expreſſed his great fear of two things, Atheiſm and Popery; and both ariſing out of our needleſs differences. By theſe the Enemies of our Religion gain this, that nothing can be eſtabliſhed by Law in the Proteſtant Religion, whoſe every part is not oppoſed by ſome or other of her own Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſors; ſo that things continuing looſe and confuſed, the Papiſts have their Opportunity to urge their way, which is attended with Order and Government: And our Religion continuing thus diſtracted and divided, ſome vile Wretches lay hold on the Arguments on one ſide to confute the other, and ſo hope at laſt to deſtroy all.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Judge</hi> Hale<hi>'s Diſcourſe of Religion</hi> p. 49. When Men ſee ſo much Heat and Paſſion, ſo much Fervour and Contention, ſuch Reproaches and Revilings, ſuch Exaſperations of Authority on either Party, ſuch mutual Proſecutions one of another, that more could not poſſibly be done between Diſſenters in thoſe points, which both agree to be Fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damental; Atheiſtical Spirits are apt to conclude, that probably thoſe points that both ſides ſuppoſed to be of greater moment, are <hi>Ejuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem Farinae,</hi> as thoſe in Conteſt, which all Men take to be ſmall and inconſiderable.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Mr.</hi> Hooker<hi>'s Eccleſiaſtical Politie,</hi> p. 18. <hi>Speaking of Atheiſtical perſons,</hi> by our Contentions their Irreligious Humour is much ſtreng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thened: Alſo by the hot perſuit of lower Controverſies among Men profeſſing Religion, and agreeing in the principal Foundation thereof, they conceive hope, that about the higher Principles themſelves, time will cauſe Alteration to grow.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="42" facs="tcp:100559:25"/>
Abner<hi>'s Plea for Accommodation,</hi> p. 41. It will caſt a ſcandal on Religion, it will open the Mouths of the Adverſaries of the Truth: <hi>The Name of God is blaſphem'd among the Gentiles through you,</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.24. The worſt ſort among them ſcoff at it, it is meat and drink to them: And the better ſort are ſtagger'd by it, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraged from coming within the pale of the Church, when they ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve Chriſtians, as Contentious, as Pagans; Believers as quarrel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome, as Inſidels.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity of Catholick Chriſtians:</hi> The many Diviſions and Animoſities, which have diſtracted and ſeparated the parts of Chriſtendom, theſe have opened the Mouths, and whet the Tongues of its profeſſed Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies to Reviling and Railings, and Prophane Scoffs againſt our Bleſſed Lord and Saviour, and his Holy Religion, and ſtifled the firſt thoughts of admitting the moſt Convincing Truths to a debate among <hi>Jews, Turks,</hi> or <hi>Pagans,</hi> and ſtopt their Ears againſt the wiſeſt Charmes: To no one cauſe can we more reaſonably impute the ſmall progreſs which Chriſtianity hath made in the World for a Thouſand years paſt. The ſame contents have a pernicious influence at home upon the Faith and Manners of thoſe within the Pale of the Church: Men are hereby too ſoon tempted into ſome degree of Sceptiſciſm about ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry material points of Chriſtian Doctrine, in which they obſerve ſo many to differ among themſelves.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Biſhop</hi> Hacket <hi>on</hi> Acts 15.39. Where many Sects ſpring up, it calls the Truth more into queſtion; and the fewer Proſelytes will be gained.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly, By bringing Men to a Lukewarmneſs and Indifferency in the great things of Religion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Biſhop</hi> Whitgift<hi>'s Letter to the Council, in</hi> Fullers <hi>Hiſt.</hi> L. 9. That in King <hi>Edwards</hi> Time, and in the beginning of Queen <hi>Elizabeths</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the heat of theſe Contentions, the Goſpel mightily prevailed. But ſince this Schiſm and Diviſion the contrary Effects have happened.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Deſign of Chriſtian.</hi> p. 236. It is too viſibly apparent to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied, that thoſe who have ſuch a ſcalding hot Zeal, [or contend ſo earneſtly] either for, or againſt things of no certainty, and no ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity,
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:100559:25"/>are many of them, as their Predeceſſors the Phariſees were, in the very other Extream, as to not a few of the weightieſt matters of Religion.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Conformiſts Plea for the Nonconformiſts,</hi> Part 4. pag. 17; It ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders the Labours of the Worthieſt ſuſpected and deſpiſed [by the contrary-minded.] The moſt uſeful, profitable, ſearching Books which the World hath moſt need of, are not as much as look'd into by many, but rejected, becauſe the Books off, <hi>F</hi>—<hi>s</hi> (as they are called;) Yea, more, if a Conformiſt have the Name of <hi>F</hi> — ſome of our Church-P— will not come nigh the door-poſts of Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Mr.</hi> Kidder<hi>'s Sermons,</hi> 1 Pet 3.11. We quarrel for Trifles, and neglect our unqueſtionable Duty to God and Man.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Doctor</hi> Burnet, <hi>Biſhop of</hi> Salisbury, Matth. 12.25. p. 5. The ill Effects of this Zeal [or Contentiouſneſs] upon our ſelves will be, That as this Temper grows upon us, all our inward ſeriouſneſs will in a great meaſure abate, and turn meerly to a Form: And, with that, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other Sins will creep in upon us; we will bear with many ill things in others, becauſe they are of our Party, whom otherwiſe we would deteſt for their ill Lives, and by Converſing much with them, we will contract at leaſt a Familiarity with their Vices, and perhaps imagine. That by our rage and heat we offer up ſome acceptable Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice to God, to compenſate for out other Diſorders.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Cauſes of Decay of Piety,</hi> p. 251. When bitter Zeal was once fermented, the Orthodoxy or Hereſie of Lives became ſoon Tearms out-dated, and Men were meaſured only by Opinions: <hi>Item p.</hi> 301. They are not much diſcompoſed, to ſee Men of no Religion, 'tis on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the having one different from their own that makes their Indig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Mr.</hi> Cook<hi>'s Sermons</hi> on <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.18. p. 24; What a ſiding is there with this and the other Zealous and Conſcientious Sect, even by thoſe that have neither Zeal, nor Conſcience, but are Deriders of both, and of ſtrict Holineſs in all ſorts of Profeſſors.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="44" facs="tcp:100559:26"/>
                  <hi>Appendix to the third part of the Friendly Debate,</hi> p. 143; Doctor <hi>Jackſon</hi> tells us the firſt ground of his diſlike to the chief Solicitors of Reformation in our Church, was the deformity of their Zeal; not moving them to redreſs known Enormities of the Common-wealth, much more material, and much more nearly concerning the Advance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Goſpel, than thoſe doubtful Controverſies of Formality, about which they ſtrove.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Biſhop</hi> Wilkins <hi>on</hi> Rom. 14.17, 18; Let a Man but indifferently look round about him, amongſt all the kinds of Parties in our times, even thoſe who in his own judgment he eſteems the beſt, and then ſay; Whether both our Common Peace, and the Power of Religion hath not ſuffered exceedingly upon the account of our Zeal in leſſer matters.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Another Miſchief, it deſtroys Charity.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Doctor</hi> Steward<hi>'s Englands Caſe,</hi> p. 26: In ſuch Diviſions as theſe, Men are extreamly apt to forget all Bonds of Peace, and for poſſeſſion ſometimes of a little ſuppoſed Truth, quit indeed their whole ſtate of Charity.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Mr.</hi> Kiddder<hi>'s</hi> Sermons, 1 Pet. 3. 11. We do indeed fiercely contend with each other, but it is becauſe we want Charity; We neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect that plain Duty, whileſt we are fond of ſome Opinion of our own, which is often falſe, and at beſt but doubtful.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Pref. to</hi> Uſher<hi>'s Body of Divinity.</hi> Men falling into Sects and Schiſms, break the Bond of Love, and fall off from the Communion of Saints, as though it were no Article of their Creed; and being in Love with their own New Tenets, they contend more for them, than any Fundamental Truths, and hate, Malign moſt bitterly and Uncharitably all thoſe that differ from them in their Opinions, though never ſo Conſcientious and Religious, as though they profeſſed not the ſame Faith, yea, ſerved not the ſame God, nor believed in the ſame Chriſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Cauſes of the Decay of Chriſtian Piety,</hi> p. 284. It is apparent in too many, That they are apt to confine even the Common Offices of
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:100559:26"/>Humanity to their own Sect; and others who do not ſo, yet ſhew ſo great partiality in diſpenſing them, as diſcovers that the Name of Chriſtian is not half ſo charming as that of their own particular Faction.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Mr.</hi> Cook<hi>'s Serm.</hi> Rom. 12.18. How dreadful is it to conſider what we may plainly obſerve, that Diſſention, Hatred, and Rancour is not ſo Violent and Irreconcileable betwixt Extream Oppoſites, who diſſent utterly (as <hi>Pagans</hi> and <hi>Chriſtians</hi> for Example) as it commonly is betwixt ſubordinate profeſſors, who agree upon Generals, and in the main Subſtance, but diſſent in Particulars. Thoſe of the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> this day rather Tolerate, do not ſo extreamly hate, <hi>a Turk,</hi> a <hi>Jew,</hi> a <hi>Pagan,</hi> as they do a <hi>Proteſtant,</hi> and ſome <hi>Proteſtants</hi> to be quit with them, do in affection and kind uſage too plainly prefer a <hi>Heathen</hi> or <hi>Mahometan</hi> before them.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Judge</hi> Hales<hi>'s Diſcourſes of Relig.</hi> p. 37. It often comes to paſs that not only the Common Bond of Charity, and of Chriſtian Love is bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken between the Profeſſors of the ſame Subſtantials in Chriſtianity, but there is moſt ordinarily much more Severity, and Perſecution and Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>placableneſs, and Irreconcileableneſs, more Endeavours to undermine, and ſupplant, and diſgrace Diſſenters, more Scorns, and vilifying, and reproach, and Inſolence one towards another in their viciſſitudes of Advantage, than there is between Men of the moſt looſe and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane Lives, and Profeſſors of Chriſtianity; between Orthodox and Hereticks; nay, between Chriſtians, and Turks, or Infidels many times.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Biſhop of</hi> Salisburies <hi>Exhortation to Peace,</hi> p. 11. <hi>Luther</hi> and <hi>Zuinglius</hi> difference about the Sacrament has raiſed ſuch an alienation, that in many places the <hi>Lutherans</hi> are no leſs, and in ſome more fierce againſt the <hi>Calviniſts,</hi> than againſt Papiſts.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Biſhop</hi> Reynold<hi>'s Brotherly Agreement,</hi> p. 8. Through the preva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency of Corruption, the Affections of good Men ſo diſſenting are of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten Alienated and Eſtranged one from another.</p>
               <p>Glanvil<hi>'s Catholick Charity,</hi> p. 8. Though I ſee never ſo much eagerneſs for an Opinion, or heat for an Indifferent Circumſtance,
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:100559:27"/>out the Conſcience of Chriſtian Love, I ſhall never call that forward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs for thoſe little things, <hi>Zeal</hi> or <hi>Religion;</hi> yea, though thoſe warm Men ſhould ſacrifice their Lives to their beloved Trifles, I ſhould not think them Martyrs, but fear rather, that they went from one fire to another, and a worſe, as 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13. 3.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Mr.</hi> Cook<hi>'s Sermons on</hi> Rom. 12.18. p. 3. Though ſome di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided Parties may in their ſeveral wayes exerciſe many Acts of true and ſubſtantial Worſhip, yet whileſt the Members thereof retain in their hearts any unpeaceable Diſpoſition, or bitter Envy (though thay call it Zeal) againſt another Party, all the Effects of their Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion muſt neceſſarily be null and void; becauſe in our Religion we can find no ſort of diſpenſation for an Uncharitable Temper.</p>
               <p>Glanvil's <hi>Catholick Char.</hi> p. 55, 56. If therefore we are Friends to Chriſtian Love, let us avoid, and oppoſe this its moſt fatal Enemy; and conſider that we ſhould exerciſe our Zeal about the neceſſary, certain things, and our Charity about the reſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>That Diviſions are Ruinous of a Church.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Bucer;</hi> I ſee, with what Art Satan doth reſiſt, [<hi>i. e.</hi> the Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion;] While he goeth about to ſtir up ſo many pernitious Conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, as well in Doctrine, as Rites. For ſurely except we remove ſo manifeſt diſhonourings of God, whereby the whole Kingdom of God may be renewed. Oh how intolerable Wrath of God ſhall be kindled againſt this Rhealm! In another place, With this crafty ſlight hath that Ancient Enemy driven miſerable <hi>Germany</hi> unto theſe preſent Calamities, wherewith they be now oppreſſed, (in King <hi>Edward</hi> the VI. dayes) God forbid, Chriſt Jeſus, I ſay, our only Saviour, forbid, that he prevail againſt <hi>England</hi> with this crafty ſubtilty.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Biſhop</hi> Andrew<hi>'s Sermon,</hi> p. 913. Let us begin with the motion for Fire from Heaven upon the <hi>Samaritans, Luke</hi> 9.55. Let us begin with that which was the beginning of all this quarrel, diſſent in Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion between the <hi>Samaritan</hi> and the <hi>Jew.</hi> We ſee the fruit of it here, and what Spirit it makes Men of, mutual and mortal hatred breaking forth upon every occaſion. And theſe two the <hi>Samaritans</hi> and the <hi>Jews</hi> made not an end of it, till it made an end of them. In <hi>Joſephus</hi> you ſhall
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:100559:27"/>ſee in the days of <hi>Claudius</hi> (<hi>Cumanus</hi> then Deputy) the very like quarrel to this here, upon the very ſame occaſion, taken up wholly by the <hi>Zelotae,</hi> and purſued hard, opened the way to the <hi>Jews</hi> War, which never ended till the utter rooting out, and deſolation of them both.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Injunct. of K.</hi> James I. <hi>to the Biſhops,</hi> 1626. One thing there is, which proves a great hinderance of this State, and not continued amongſt the people without great offence againſt God, detriment both to Church and State, and our great diſſervice in this and all other buſineſs: It is the breach of Unity which is grown too great and common amongſt all ſorts of men: The danger of this goes far; for in all States it has made way for enemies to enter.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Mr.</hi> Hookers <hi>Anſwer to Mr.</hi> Travers <hi>Supplicat.</hi> p. 30. There can come nothing of Contention, but the natural waſte of the parties con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending, till a common Enemy dance in the aſhes of them both.</p>
               <p>Halls <hi>Works, Biſhop of</hi> Norwich, <hi>p.</hi> 413. If we deſire the grief of our common Mother, the languiſhing of the Goſpel, the extirpation of Religion, the loſs of Poſterity, the advantage of our Adverſaries, which way could theſe be effected more, than by our Diviſions?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Mr.</hi> Venues <hi>Plea for Peace,</hi> p. 25. Falling out among our ſelves we ſtand aloof off one from another, ſuffering our ſelves to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured by the common Foe, while we look on: Yea happily we ſhall be ready to act one againſt another, and ſo to ſave the Enemy a la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour; as <hi>Moab</hi> againſt <hi>Ammon,</hi> and <hi>Ammon</hi> againſt <hi>Moab,</hi> and <hi>Edom</hi> againſt both, ſheathing their Swords each in other; ſo that <hi>Jehoſaphat.</hi> and his <hi>Jews</hi> needed not to ſtrike a ſtroke, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 20.3. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 9.21. <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.15. It is a <hi>Dutch</hi> device, and a good one, to this purpoſe, of two earthen pots ſwimming on the water, <hi>frangimur ſi collidimur,</hi> we are broken all to pieces if we claſh one againſt another. <hi>Idem,</hi> p. 31. Beſides that God doth often puniſh breaches and diviſions in the Church among Chriſtians, by raiſing up ſome ſtorm againſt them, which may teach them better to agree; we being in this too like to Sheep, which on a fair Sun-ſhine day are ſcattered each from other up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Mountains; but a ſtorm brings them together: So doth <hi>Euſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hius</hi> relate, that the Church enjoyed much peace and freedom imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:100559:28"/>before the Perfection raiſed againſt it by <hi>Diocleſian;</hi> and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king no better uſe of it than to fall aſunder into Diviſions and Facti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Contentions, inſtantly God took a courſe by way of puniſhment to cover the Daughter of <hi>Zion</hi> with a Cloud in his Anger, and to caſt down from Heaven to Earth the beauty of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and not to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member his footſtool in the day of his Anger, ſetting up the Right-hand of his Churches enemies, and making their adverſaries to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce. <hi>Lam.</hi> 2.1. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 39.42.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Mr.</hi> Ward <hi>of</hi> Ipſwich<hi>'s Sermons,</hi> p. 253. Charity, Charity is the builder of Churches: Strife about trifles hath waſted many famous ones, and placed the Temple of <hi>Mahomet</hi> where the Golden Candle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtick was wont to ſtand. We pity the former Ages contending about leavened and unleavened Bread, Keeping of <hi>Eaſter,</hi> Faſting on Sun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>days, the future Ages will do the like by us.</p>
               <p>Pygots Abuers <hi>Plea for Accommodation in</hi> 43. p. 33. Take heed, your private diſſentions do not expoſe you as a prey to the common adverſary. I remember the dying Fathers admonition to his Sons: Having call'd them all together, he cauſed a Faggot to be brought into the Room, and commanded the ſtouteſt of them to break it; they tryed one after another, but none of them could do it, then he bade them undo the band, and take them ſtick by ſtick, and ſo they ſnapped them aſunder like a twined thread: Thus ſhall it be with you, my Sons, (ſaith the Old Man) when I am dead, if you continue united and knit together in the bond of Peace and Love, no Enemies ſhall be able to hurt you; but if you once break the bond, and fall into differences among your ſelves, you'l preſently be broken to pieces, and come to nothing. <hi>Item,</hi> p. 42. The wild Boar of the Foreſt, I mean the <hi>Turk,</hi> had never made ſuch inrodes into <hi>Chriſtendom,</hi> had it not been for the diſſention of Chriſtian Brethren.</p>
               <p>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon the Rebellion in</hi> Ireland, <hi>Ejac.</hi> 3. Becauſe we have not more loved thy Truth, and practiced in Charity, thou haſt ſuffered a Spirit of error and bitterneſs, of mutual and mortal hatred to ariſe among us.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Biſhop</hi> Reynolds <hi>Broth. Agreement,</hi> p. 18. Cites holy <hi>Cyprian,</hi> who in his time looked upon it as one great cauſe of that ſore Perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution,
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:100559:28"/>which God ſent upon the Church: Had Unanimity and Peace, ſaid he, been amongſt the Brethren, we had long ago obtained our Petitions from Divine Mercy, neither had we been thus long toſſed with thoſe Tempeſts, which endanger our Faith and Salvation: <hi>Imo vero nec veniſſent Fratribus haec mala, ſi in unum fraternitas at fuiſſet animata.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Biſhop</hi> Hacket <hi>on</hi> Acts 15.39. <hi>p.</hi> 8, 9. The paſſage is well known about <hi>Conſtantine</hi> the Great, how he remov'd from his Palace in the <hi>Eaſt,</hi> becauſe every corner of the Imperial City was filled with ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe diſputations about Religion; much more you may preſume that God will depart from that Church, where the flames of notorious diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cords are.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Cauſes of decay of Chriſtian Piety,</hi> p. 304. As to the extirpation of the <hi>Eaſtern</hi> Churches, he that ſhall examine the Records of thoſe Times will have cauſe to ſay, their janglings and diviſions were not only in a Moral and Divine, but even in a proper natural ſence the Inſtruments of it, the <hi>Turk,</hi> only coming in at thoſe breaches which themſelves have made.</p>
               <p>Glanvells <hi>Cath. Charity,</hi> p. 17. The greateſt evils that have, or can happen to the Church, have been the effects of the decay of Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, and of thoſe inteſtine diviſions that have grown up in it: From theſe ſhe hath always ſuffered more, than from external Perſecutions. The flames within have conſumed her, when thoſe from without have only ſing'd her garments.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Biſhop of</hi> Salisbury<hi>'s Exhort, to Peace and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion, on</hi> Matth. 12.25. <hi>p.</hi> 3. There is nothing that defeats the end of Religion more, and doth more naturally lead to all manner of ſin and impieties, which, muſt end in Temporal as well as Eternal ruine, then our Diviſions, <hi>Pag.</hi> 9. In Diviſions either party will be ſo intent on their little de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns, that the whole may periſh; and they will bite and devour one another, till they are either conſumed one of another, or made an eaſie Conqueſt to thoſe that both ſee and improve all their advantages.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Item, Exhort.</hi> p. 10, 11. The. <hi>Africans</hi> continued quarrelling a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout <hi>Cecilian</hi> and his ordainers, till the <hi>Vandals</hi> came and deſtroyed
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:100559:29"/>both the one and the other. <hi>Item,</hi> p. 11. And can we think without aſtoniſhment, that the difference of the Proceſſion of the Holy Ghoſt could ever have rent the <hi>Greek</hi> and <hi>Latin</hi> Churches ſo violently one from another, that the <hi>Latins</hi> rather than aſſiſt the other, look'd on till they were deſtroyed by the <hi>Ottoman</hi> Family, which has ever ſince been ſo terrible a Neighbour to the reſt of <hi>Europe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Mr.</hi> Hesketh <hi>on</hi> Lam 3.20, 21. <hi>p.</hi> 25. It were ſeaſonable to have made ſome reflections upon the unchriſtian heats and unreaſonable dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferences that are among us, things that render us not only ſinners, but great fools, and plain contrivers for our own Ruine. For theſe are evils, that will deſtroy us alone, and by their own weight ſink us into deſtruction. Divided Societies laſt not long, the experience of all Ages confirms it for a Truth; and I do not ſee what reaſon we have to expect an exemption from the common fate.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Dr.</hi> Mores <hi>Myſtery of Iniquity,</hi> p. 554. What harm is it to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage ſo well of the Reformation, as that after the decurſion of the years of their Childhood, God will ripen them into a more Manly ſence of the great and indiſpenſable Duties of the Goſpel; that he will not tolerate nor connive any longer at their Childiſh ſquabling about Nut-ſhells, Counters and Cherry-ſtones; and menace them even with deſtruction, if they leave not off their animoſities and aſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rities of mind about toys and trifles, and hold faſt to the Royal Law of Love? <hi>If ye bite and worry one another, take heed that ye be not conſumed one of another.</hi> Gal. 5.15.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Mr.</hi> Hancocks <hi>Sermon on</hi> Luke 19.42. If the judgments of God, which we have already groaned under, cannot; ſure the dangers that threaten us and our Religion, might help to abate our heats, and ſuppreſs our differences: Did not Chriſtianity decay in the Church of <hi>Corinth</hi> as their Schiſms and Factions increaſed? <hi>Pag.</hi> 31. Were not the former Conqueſts of theſe Nations, the effects of our own Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions? God grant that ſaying may never be applyed to us, which was uſed of our Fore-Fathers, that whilſt they ſeverally quarrel'd among themſelves, they were all overcome by the common Enemy. <hi>Item,</hi> They are convinced, that a number of petty Sects and divided Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſts cannot long maintain their ground againſt the <hi>Roman</hi> Forces.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="51" facs="tcp:100559:29"/>
                  <hi>Mr.</hi> Cooks <hi>Sermon on</hi> Rom. 12.18. <hi>p.</hi> 4. Were it not for that ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curity, <hi>the gates of Hell ſhall not prevail againſt it,</hi> (that is the Church) the unhappy contentions about it, the worſt of Devils would ſoon haſten its deſtruction.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Mr.</hi> Jekylls <hi>Sermon on</hi> 5.29. <hi>p.</hi> 21. But there is one thing, which if not ſpeedily prevented, will before we are aware let in that which we ſo much fear, and cry out againſt; (<hi>viz.</hi> Popery) and which perhaps too too many of us, more or leſs, may be acceſſary to; I mean thoſe unnatural heats and diviſions amongſt our ſelves, amidſt which, though we are not altogether ſwerved from the Form, yet we are ſtrangely degenerated from the true Spirit and Power of God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs and Chriſtianity. — How ſad the effect and conſequence of theſe heart-burnings and animoſities, unchriſtian ſtrifes and debates will be, I am afraid to think of! <hi>Item,</hi> p. 25. We are diſtracting our own Devotions, yea and provoking (I had almoſt ſaid devouring) one another, whilſt our Adverſaries in the day they look for (which God grant may never come) will make no difference, but ſwallow us up together.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Principles and Practices,</hi> p. 10. <hi>of Ep.</hi> It is high time to be recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciled to Moderation and Sobriety, to lay aſide our uncharitable, and therefore unchriſtian heats againſt each other, and to throw water up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on thoſe flames, that threaten our deſtruction, (and but for Gods in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite Mercy, would have effected it before now) inſtead of adding more fewel unto it.</p>
               <p>Mr. <hi>Kidder</hi> on 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.11. <hi>p.</hi> 29. The ſeveral Sects and Quarrels of the <hi>Jews</hi> among themſelves, and the fury of their Zealots, were but a prologue to their miſerable deſtruction.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Biſhop</hi> Taylors <hi>Coll. of Diſcourſes, Ep. before Liberty of Proph.</hi> For my own particular, I cannot but expect that God in his Juſtice ſhould enlarge the bounds of the <hi>Turkiſh</hi> Empire, or ſome other way puniſh Chriſtians, by reaſon of their pertinacious diſputings about things un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neceſſary, undeterminable and unprofitable.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Cauſes of the Decay of Chriſtian Piety,</hi> p. 427. It is the uſual Oeconomy of Divine Juſtice to make our Crimes our Puniſhment,
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:100559:30"/>and to give us up to thoſe ills, which were at firſt our own depraved choice: And God knows, we have too much reaſon to fear this may be our caſe; that we who have ſo perverſly violated all the bonds of Unity, wantonly wrangled our ſelves out or all inclinations to Peace, ſhould never be able to reſume them. <hi>Item,</hi> p. 428. This, alaſs! as it is the fearfulleſt, ſo is it the probableſt iſſue of our wild conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions; ſuch as nothing but the miraculous effluxes of Divine Clemen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy can avert.</p>
               <p>To conclude, as well we may, with this as an undoubted Truth, from Mr. <hi>Kidders</hi> Sermon on 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.11. <hi>p.</hi> 22. Theſe Contentions have done more miſchief than all the Perſecutions put together; more have fallen, and more dangerouſly this way, than by the Swords of Tyrants, and avowed Enemies of our Religion.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Arguments for taking the Ceremonies away, or leaving the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe of them indifferent; eſpecially the Sign of the Croſs.</head>
               <p>HEre is the moſt proper place to premiſe ſomewhat concerning the Lawfulneſs of Ceremonies, leaſt I ſhould in any thing which follows be thought to condemn my own practice, in point of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity to theſe Ceremonies.</p>
               <p>As to Kneeling at the Sacrament, I think the Rubrick ſhould ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfie Perſons; it ſpeaks very plainly: It is hereby declared, that no Adoration is intended, or ought to be done, either unto the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mental Bread and Wine, there Bodily received, or unto any Corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>real Preſence of Chriſts Natural Fleſh and Blood. For the Sacramen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal Bread and Wine remain ſtill in their very Natural Subſtances,
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:100559:30"/>and therefore may not be Adored, (for that were Idolatry to be ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horred of all faithful Chriſtians) and the Natural Body and Blood of our Saviour Chriſt are in Heaven, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Mr.</hi> Bayns <hi>Chriſtian Letters,</hi> p. 201. Kneeling is neither an occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, nor by participation Idolatry. Kneeling never bred Bread-Worſhip, and our Doctrine of the Sacrament known to all the World, doth free us from ſuſpition of Adoration in it. Thus he though a Nonconformiſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Mr.</hi> Tombs <hi>Theodulia,</hi> p. 168. That whatſoever Geſture our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour uſed it doth not oblige us, becauſe the Geſture ſeems not to have been of choice uſed by Chriſt. 2. Becauſe St. <hi>Paul</hi> omits the Geſture, which he would not have done, if it had been binding. 3. He men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions the Night, and calls it the Lords Supper; and if the Time be not neceſſary, much leſs the Geſture. 4. If the Geſture doth oblige, then Chriſtians muſt uſe the ſelf-ſame that Chriſt uſed, <hi>i. e.</hi> Lying down or Leaning, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> in this <hi>Chriſtian Directory</hi> (I think ſpeaking of the Sacrament) tells us, he thinks Mr <hi>Paybodies</hi> Book in defence of <hi>Kneeling</hi> to unanſwerable.</p>
               <p>As to the Surplice; <hi>Platina</hi> mentions it to be brought in very ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly into the Church, in the days of the good Biſhops of <hi>Rome, Anno Domini</hi> 250, by <hi>Stephen,</hi> a Martyr under <hi>Decius</hi> the Emperour; And none can deny but that in the Apoſtles days, after Baptiſm (the Baptized in thoſe hot Countries of the <hi>Eaſt,</hi> being commonly at leaſt dipped or plunged in the Water with their naked Bodies) the perſons Baptized put on new white Veſtments to ſhew the Purity of a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian: Whence the Lords day after <hi>Eaſter</hi> (which <hi>Eaſter</hi> was their chief time of Baptizing) was called <hi>Dominica in Albis,</hi> the Lords day in White. <hi>Mr.</hi> Leighs <hi>Annotations on the New Teſtament</hi> tell you thoſe expreſſions of putting on, the Lord Jeſus, and putting off the Old Man have alluſion to the Garments. <hi>Peter Martyr</hi> ſpeaks in his Anſwer to Biſhop <hi>Hoopers</hi> Letter: The Defenders of this Ceremony may pretend ſome honeſt and juſt ſignification, and <hi>Zepperus</hi> himſelf, (though no Friend to the Sign of the Croſs in the Baptiſmal Office, as Mr. <hi>Sprint</hi> tells us in his <hi>Caſſander Anglicanus</hi>) ſpeaking of the Papiſts, ſaith thus; We read nothing of the Superſtitious Habits in the Monu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of Antiquity, except only of the White Veſture; <hi>Qua uſi
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:100559:31"/>ſunt ſine ſuperſtitione in ſignum &amp; Commone factionem honeſtatis vitae.</hi> So that if it were a ſignificative Ceremony (as it is not in the Church of <hi>Englands</hi> uſe of it) yet in their judgments the uſe of it might be innocent.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Biſhop</hi> Taylors <hi>Ductor Dubitantium,</hi> p. 668. Great Reaſon have we to honour the Wiſdom of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> which hath in all her Offices retained but one Ritual or Ceremony that is not of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Ordinance, or Apoſtolical Practice, and that is the Croſs at Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm: Which, though it be a ſignificant Ceremony, and of no other uſe, yet as it is a compliance with the Antient Church, ſo is it very innocent in it ſelf, and being one alone is not troubleſome [or burthen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome]. Archbiſhop <hi>Whitgift</hi> ſaid, the Surplice was not enjoyned as a ſignificant Ceremony. The Canon about the Surplice mentioneth nothing of uſing it for ſignification of purity or unſpotted innocency. We do not wear it as monitory or inſtructive to keep the inner man pure and clean, but as a Garment of uſe in the Antient Church, and tranſmitted down from them to us, and retained at our Reformation: And ſome urge it to be decent, and no ways unbecoming a Miniſter of the Goſpel, who may wear certainly White as lawfully as Black, without placing Holyneſs or Unholyneſs in any Garment. If we ſee not ſo great reaſon for the impoſition or continuance, yet we may ſee ſufficient reaſon for the ſubmiſſion. It is not uſed by us as by the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts, who muſt have it hallowed or conſecrated by Praying over it, that it may defend him that wears it from the Devil. They uſe it indeed with a Superſtitious opinion of Holyneſs, but we have no Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecrating Surplices, nor any ſuch opinion that it is a fence againſt the Devil, or preſervative from his aſſaults and temptations.</p>
               <p>Several Nonconformiſts have ſaid, they would be content to Preach the Goſpel in a Fools coat rather than be ſilent; as the Famous Mr. <hi>Daille</hi> of <hi>France</hi> being asked his judgment by ſome Nonconfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſts of <hi>England,</hi> ſaid (as I am told by a <hi>French</hi> Miniſter, and that he had ſeen it mentioned in a Book wrote by one of our Biſhops) That our Ceremonies <hi>were good,</hi> and before he would make a rent in the Church for ſuch things as the Surplice, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> If the King of <hi>France</hi> would give him leave to Preach at <hi>Paris,</hi> (which the King forbid him) he would Preach, though it were in a Fools coat.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="55" facs="tcp:100559:31"/>
As to the Lawfulneſs of the Sign of the Croſs at Baptiſm, It is, I Baptize, I Baptize thee in the Name of the Father, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> which is all that is Eſſential to Baptiſm, or the Subſtance of that Ordinance: Then it follows, We receive this [Baptized] Child into the Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation of Chriſts Flock, as the Priviledge. Baptiſm makes him a Member of the Catholick Church, and particularly of that Church into which he is Baptized: But the owning and receiving into Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion is the Churches Act. Then follows, and ſign him with the Sign of the Croſs in token, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> as ſignificative, and with the words decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rative of that Duty, which he is obliged and bound unto by Baptiſm, to own the Faith of Chriſt Crucified, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And though the Words are, In token that he ſhall not be aſhamed to own, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> It is only in the Judgment of Charity, what the Church hopeth and expecteth from him hereafter, when he is come to years to know Good and Evil, his Faith, Profeſſion, and Obedience to the Trinity, according to his Baptiſm. And thus Dr. <hi>Bourges</hi> in his Subſcription with Expli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of his meaning, allowed by King <hi>James</hi> the Firſt, and the Arch-Biſhop of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> and declared to be the ſenſe of the Church of <hi>England:</hi> Where the Book ſaith, And do ſign him with the Sign of the Croſs, in token, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> I underſtand, ſaith he, that Book not to mean, That the Sign of the Croſs hath any Vertue in it to effect or further this Duty, but only to intimate and expreſs by that Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony (by which the Ancients did avow their profeſſion of Chriſt Crucified) what the Congregation hopeth and expecteth hereafter from that Infant: And therefore alſo when the Twentieth Canon ſaith, That the Infant is by that Sign Dedicated unto the Service of Chriſt, I underſtand that Dedication to import, not a real Conſecra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Child, which was done in Baptiſm it ſelf; but only a Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonial Declaration of that Dedication, like as the Prieſt is ſaid to make clean the Leper, whoſe being clean he only declared.</p>
               <p>There was undoubtedly a lawful uſe of the Croſs in ſome Primitive Chriſtians, while they lived among profeſſed <hi>Jews</hi> and <hi>Heathens,</hi> Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies of the Croſs of Chriſt, as <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.18. upbraiding the Chriſtians that their God dyed upon a Croſs. It began at his Crucifixion, <hi>Matth.</hi> 27.41, 42; <hi>The Chief Prieſts mocking him with the Scribes and Elders ſaid, If he be the King of Iſrael, let him now come down from the Croſs, and we will believe him.</hi> The more others ſcoffed at the Chriſtians for their Crucified Saviour, with the greater Courage, Reſolution, and
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:100559:32"/>Conſtancy did the Chriſtians own and make profeſſion of him. And this was a ſign profeſſing Chriſt, which at the ſight of <hi>Jews</hi> and <hi>Infidels,</hi> in the Markets, and any where elſe was of common uſe among the Chriſtians, uſed at their Meals many times, and Tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to Baptiſm. When the Empire became Chriſtian, <hi>Conſtantine</hi> uſed it, and others in their Enſigns of War, to ſignifie, Chriſt Cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cified was the God they owned, and expected Victory in Battel from him. In their Coats of Arms, in their Coynes at this day, it is uſed as of Old, to ſhew the Religion of the Perſons, or the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries, that they were Chriſtians. If any Object that was a Civil uſe of it, and not Religious, I ſay it was of Religious ſignification there. Yet indeed with <hi>Peter Martyr,</hi> for mine own part, I wiſh that all things may be done ſimpliciſſime, moſt free from Humane mixtures in the Worſhip of God; Again, Its ſignification and uſe is, <hi>ad homi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem,</hi> and not <hi>ad Deum.</hi> For firſt, If it were permanent, and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>printed on the Forhead (which in Scripture is uſed to ſignifie boldneſs and confidence, in a good, and in all ill ſenſe, as <hi>Ezek.</hi> 3.8. <hi>Jer.</hi> 3.3. And ſo the ſign of the Croſs made there ſignifieth of the Child boldneſs, Chriſtian Courage and Confidence, that he ſhall not be aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>) it would ſignifie to Men, and not to God; unto Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, that he was one of their number. Secondly, The uſe of it among the Primitive Chriſtians was to ſignifie to Chriſtians among themſelves, or more eſpecially to Jews and Heathens their Chriſtian Profeſſion. Thirdly, The Diſſenters call them ſignificant teaching ſigns, and bring that as an Argument againſt them, but do we teach God or Man, ſurely Man is fit for Inſtruction. And as to Addition, the Curſe is equally againſt diminiſhing, as adding: But the Love<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kiſs, <hi>Signaculum reconciliationis;</hi> Waſhing the Diſciples Feet a token of Humility; The Feaſts of Charity mention'd at the Sacrament by St. <hi>Jude;</hi> the Community of Goods, the Deaconeſſes, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Things of this Nature are not of the ſubſtance of the Word, or the Ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, but are Circumſtantials, and may be changed, added, or taken away ſafely. I could cite too an Eminent Nonconformiſt, where he ſaith, it cannot be called an Addition in Scripture ſenſe, unleſs the Governours ſtamp Holyneſs upon it, or Neceſſity, as a neceſſary Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, Doctrinal Neceſſity he means: Or unleſs by adding they mean, giving the ſame Efficacy to Humane Inſtitutions as God doth to his, by making them to confer Grace upon the rightly diſpoſed; and by di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſhing that the Service is not compleat without it. I ſhall conclude
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:100559:32"/>with a ſaying of Mr. <hi>Calvin, Let not any think me ſo auſtere or bound up, as to forbid a Chriſtian to accommodate himſelf to the Papiſts, in any Ceremony or Obſervance: For it is not my purpoſe to condemn any thing, but what is clearly Evil, and openly Vitious.</hi> I have ſaid thus much, leſt ſome that are uncharitable to our Church ſhould think, I wrote, Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe I was pinched, and could not tell how to ſatisfie my Conſcience in Conformity.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Doctor</hi> More<hi>'s Myſtery of Godlineſs,</hi> Pref. Sect. 10. The Croſs, ſo ſeaſonable at the firſt Inſtitution of it, while profeſſed Pagans, were mingled among Chriſtians, and ſo ſignificant alwayes, that if the Church cannot make ſuch an Additional as this (in his Judgment) ſhe can make none at all.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>True State of Prim. Chriſt.</hi> p. 18; I will name another Ceremony, which gives great offence with greater reaſon; the bowing towards the Altar, which in my own Judgment I allow, and practiſe in ſome meaſure, when I come into ſuch Congregations as generally uſe it, avoiding ſtill to give offence to any, as far as I may with ſafe Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience. I affirm it is a very fitting thing to ſhew Reverence in the Houſe of God, and to ſhew it by bowing as well as any other means, and to bow that way, to the Eaſt as well as any other way: Bowing towards the Altar is grown into abuſe, by the Papiſts ſuppoſing Chriſt to be Corporally preſent there. With us the Miniſter bows to ſhew ſome, particular Reverence in that place, where the Bleſſed Sacrament is Conſecrated. Let this paſs for good, though ſomething alſo may be ſaid againſt it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Ceremonies not to be Innovated or Multiplyed.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>BIſhop</hi> Taylor<hi>'s Ductor Dubit.</hi> L. 3. Ch. 4. Rule 4. Sect. 19, 20. That this Rule of Order and Decency is not to be extended to ſuch Decencies as are only Ornament, but is to be limited to ſuch as only reſcue from Confuſion; the reaſon is, becauſe the Prelates and
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:100559:33"/>Spiritual Guides cannot do their Duty, unleſs things be ſo orderly, as that there be no Confuſion, but if it can go beyond this Limit, then it can have no Natural Limit, but may extend to Sumptuouſneſs, to Ornament for Churches, to rich Utenſils, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> But becauſe this is too ſubject to abuſe, and gives a Secular Power over Mens Eſtates, and is not any part of Spiritual Government, it's more than Chriſt gave to Miniſters. <hi>Id. Rules to his Clergy.</hi> 39. R. Let no Miniſter of a Pariſh introduce any Beremony, Rites or Geſtures, though with ſome ſeeming Piety and Devotion, but what are commanded by the Church, and Eſtabliſhed by Law, and let theſe alſo be wiſely and uſefully Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicated to the People, that they may underſtand the Reaſons and Meaſures of Obedience, but let there be no more introduced, leſt the People be burthened unneceſſarily, and tempted, or divided.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Idem,</hi> And though ſignificant Ceremonies may be for Edification, yet it is to be conſidered, whether the introducing of ſuch things does not deſtroy the Church, not only in her Chriſtian Liberty, but in the Simplicity and Purity, and Spirituality of her Religion, by inſenſibly changing it into a Ceremonial and External Service.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>True State of the Primitive Church,</hi> p. 18. With us the Miniſter bows at the Altar, to ſhew ſome particular Reverence in that place, where the Bleſſed Sacrament is Conſecrated; though ſomething may be ſaid againſt that: Yet I pray tell me, Why the Reader paſſing from one ſide of the Church to the other, and the Miniſter paſſing from one end of the Altar to the other, bows again. I verily believe 'tis meerly a cauſeleſs Cuſtom taken up one from another, (the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon beginning of all Superſtitions) having no reaſon for it, but much againſt it, giving thereby great ſcandal to weak ones, and ground of ſlaunder to malitious ones, who lay hold on any occaſions to accuſe them of Papiſtry. For certainly it is done with little or no Reaſon, or with a great deal of Superſtition.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Serious and Compaſſionate Enquiry,</hi> &amp;c. To do all that I may without danger to my ſelf, and not at all to regard what others can comply with; or to uſe my own Liberty to the offence of others, is to be Unchriſtian and Uncharitable. And in this ſence only are we to underſtand all the Diſcourſes of the Apoſtle about Scandal and Offence, where there is <hi>Materia libera.</hi> For he that will provoke his Brother to ſin, by do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:100559:33"/>that which he may omit without ſin, is guilty of ſin in ſo doing. <hi>It.</hi> p. 245. To the end that we may prevail with them to deny themſelves in ſomethings for the Publick Good, we ſhould do well to give them Examples of our own Self-denyal, and abridging our own Liberty, in Condeſcention to them in ſuch things as are not the matter of the Law; and that we will not out-run the Laws, to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradict and vex them, in what we may forbear without ſin.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Doctor</hi> Barrow<hi>'s Sermons of Love,</hi> p. 181. An Act of Charity to abſtain from any thing, which either may occaſion him to commit Sin, or diſaffect him to Religion, or diſcourage him in the practice of Duty, or which any wiſe may diſcompoſe, vex, or grieve him, (the Apoſtle having ſaid) <hi>That if thy Brother be not grieved with thy Meat, now walkeſt thou not Charitably, Rom.</hi> 14.15.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="arguments">
            <pb n="60" facs="tcp:100559:34"/>
            <head>Having premiſed ſomewhat in Defence of the Ceremonies, and againſt Innovations <hi>&amp;c.</hi> I ſhall proceed to thoſe <hi>Arguments for leaving the Uſe of the Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies Indifferent.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <hi>ARG<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>MENT</hi> I.</p>
            <p>COnſider firſt, That by leaving the Ceremonies Indifferent, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formiſts have their Liberty allowed them to uſe them. Where Miniſters ſcruple the uſe of that ſign of the Croſs, but the Parents are for it, they may get any Neighbouring Miniſter that is of the ſame Opinion to Baptize their Child after their manner. If their Parents be againſt it, the Miniſter holding it but a thing indifferent, why may he not forbear the uſe of it for ſatisfaction of the Parents?</p>
            <p n="2">II. I do not read of any that lived and dyed Nonconformiſts, but ſcrupled the Sign of the Croſs, which ſhows they are not ſatisfied in Conſcience about it: But our Conſciences will bear the yielding of it up for Peace, becauſe we hold Ceremonies to be <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, things In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different, in themſelves neither good nor evil. If indifferent, let us not contend ſo earneſtly for their uſe, as for neceſſary things, and matters of Faith, but manifeſt an indifferency for their Continuance, or Abrogation.</p>
            <p n="3">III. The Ceremonies are <hi>inutilia Coelo,</hi> of little or no uſe for the winning of Souls; and I ſee not but that Prelates Speech was truly Chriſtian, who ſaid we had rather loſe a Ceremony than a Soul. As it was ſaid of ſome Meats, neither if we eat them, are we the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, nor if we eat not, are we the worſe; ſo we are nothing better'd by theſe Ceremonies. Indifferent things have no Spiritual Vertue or Efficacy in them. We do not hold with the Papiſts that Surplices, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:100559:34"/>hallowed defend him that wears them from the Devil. And Canon Thirty, ſaith, that the Sign of the Croſs doth neither add any thing to the Vertue and Perfection of Baptiſm: Nor being omitted, doth detract any thing from the Effect and Subſtance of it.</p>
            <p n="4">IV. The Reaſon for the firſt uſe of the Ceremonies ceaſeth much. They were kept, partly out of Compliance with the Papiſts, to gain upon them, becauſe the People could not be ſo wholly drawn off from the uſe of the Sign of the Croſs; and ſomewhat too out of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliance with the Primitive Chriſtians, who uſed the Sign of the Croſs often, and very early after the Apoſtles dayes, as <hi>Juſtin Martyr</hi> ſaith, <hi>in foro, in agris.</hi> And thus the Church of <hi>England</hi> ſhowed ſhe left the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> only in her Innovations, and would go along with her in what the Ancient Church practiſed, that ſhe might be the more inexcuſable, and juſtly condemned, if ſhe rejected Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with us. But now the caſe is altered, the Papiſts are hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by it, and encouraged, upbraiding us (as Biſhop <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſher</hi> ſaid of them) If your Fleſh be not good, why do you drink of our Broth? But our Proteſtant Brethren ſtumble at it, and it is diſuſed by other Reformed Churches; and therefore in condeſcention to the weakneſs of the one, and Uniformity with the other Reformed Churches, perhaps it were to be wiſhed that now the uſe of it were forborn.</p>
            <p n="5">V. Againſt the Impoſition of the Ceremonies is becauſe of the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Objections againſt them, eſpecially againſt the Croſs, as a ſignificant Ceremony, not inſtituted by Chriſt; as a Dedicating Covenanting Sign, as a Sacramental Sign, or as having the ſemblance of a Sacrament, or againſt the uſe of it in that place immediately after Baptiſm, and the Duties of the Baptized more expreſly affixed to that Sign, than to the Sacrament it ſelf; as a <hi>mediunt cultus.</hi> Again, as Superſtitious and Scandalous, becauſe of the Popiſh abuſe of it; as a curſed Addition to the Word of God, and the Sacrament of Baptiſm; as impoſed on Miniſters and Children of thoſe Parents that ſcruple, and are not ſatisfied in Conſcience about the uſe of it, as well as thoſe that are; as the Likeneſs and Image of Chriſt Crucified; forbidden ſay they in the Second Commandment; as will Worſhip, as diſuſed in other Proteſtant Churches; as againſt Chriſtian Liberty, as unſuitable to the ſimplicity of the Goſpel, as needleſs, unprofitable, and cauſing Diviſions in the Church. Although none of the Objections, or Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:100559:35"/>that I can find againſt it, convince me that the ſubmiſſion to it, and the uſe of it is utterly unlawful, yet it ſhould ſeem incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venient to continue a thing which hath ſo plauſible and numerous Objections againſt it.</p>
            <p n="6">VI. For making ſome allowances in reſpect of the Ceremonies; God himſelf diſpenſeth with his own Commands about Rituals, or ſmaller matters in caſe of neceſſity, or when great good or hurt ſtands on the other ſide to outweigh them. 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 21.6. <hi>David</hi> in his hunger eats the Shewbread, which only the Prieſts were to eat, and Chriſt on the ſame account lets the Diſciples pluck and rub the ears of Corn on the Sabbath-day, 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 8.64. <hi>Solomon</hi> hallows the middle of the Court for an Altar, becauſe the Brazen Altar of the Lord was too little for the Offerings. A multitude did eat the Paſſover otherwiſe than appointed, 2 <hi>Chron</hi> 30.18. on the Second Moneth; for they could not keep it at the time appointed, as the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond and Third Verſes. An Ox or an Aſs is to be watered, or pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led out of a Pit on the Sabbath day: <hi>Periculum vitae diſſolvit Sabba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum,</hi> (as the Proverb ſays) though by many good Men, a matter of Controverſie, or thought to be Moral and not Ceremonial. Surely then leſſer matters upon great and weighty Occaſions, when Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tually neceſſary for the Churches Good and Peace, and for the La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours of able Men in the Work of the Miniſtry, may very well be diſpenſed with. For Humane Ceremonies cannot pretend to a like Authority, or Neceſſity, much leſs a greater than thoſe of Divine appointment.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>That Ceremonies muſt yield to ſubſtance.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, Or, <hi>King</hi> James I. <hi>Inſtructions to his Son,</hi> p. 15. Learn wiſely to diſcern between points of Salvation and indifferent things, betwixt Subſtance and Ceremonies: As for the latter ſpare not to uſe, or alter them, as the neceſſity of the Times ſhall require.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Biſhop</hi> Halls <hi>Works,</hi> p. 1092. Our Saviour juſtifies the act of <hi>Abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>melechs</hi> giving <hi>David</hi> Holy Bread and the Sword: Ceremonies muſt give place to Subſtance; God will have Mercy and not Sacrifice: Charity is the ſumme and the end of the Law; that muſt be aimed at in all our actions.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="63" facs="tcp:100559:35"/>
               <hi>Biſhop</hi> Taylors <hi>Duct. Dubit.</hi> p. 735. Thus if a Church commands ſuch Ceremonies to be uſed, ſuch Orders, ſuch Prayers, they are to be obſerved when they may; but if I fall into the hands of an enemy to that manner or Worſhip, who will kill, or afflict me greatly for uſing it, I am in that caſe diſobliged, [even as <hi>Periculum vitae diſſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vit Sabbatum</hi>].</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Serious and Compaſſionate Enquiry,</hi> p. 159. On <hi>Davids</hi> eating the Shew-bread; It is ſufficiently intimated, that God doth not only pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer Moral acts before Ceremonial, but alſo doth make great allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ances, limitations and exceptions in the one caſe and not in the other: For it is as if our Saviour had ſaid; Had you cenſorious Phariſees un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood either God or Religion, you would have known that ſo long as there is not Contumacy and Contempt in the neglect of thoſe Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuals, but the excuſe of a juſt neceſſity, or the Rational Conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of a greater good to preponderate the omiſſion, God doth not impute it for a ſin.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Biſhop</hi> Saunderſon <hi>on</hi> Rom. 3.8. <hi>Sect.</hi> 31. Affirmative Duties do not <hi>obligare ad ſemper</hi> (as being many it is impoſſible they ſhould.) And many times Duties otherwiſe neceſſary, in caſe of Superiour Reaſon and Duties, do ceaſe to be neceſſary <hi>pro hic &amp; nunc;</hi> and then to omit them is not to do evil.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Biſhop</hi> Wilkins, <hi>p.</hi> 413, 414. Now Divine Laws themſelves are capable of relaxation, which is the meaning of that Proverbial ſaying ſo frequent in Scripture, That God will have Mercy and not Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice; and therefore much more will Humane Laws admit it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>True ſtate of the Primitive Church.</hi> As to Ceremonies, I wonder men of any tolerable diſcretion ſhould be ſo eager either for or againſt them, our Salvation no ways depending on them, but much hazarded by our contentions about them, breaking Peace, the principal thing recommended to us by the Goſpel of Peace.</p>
            <p n="8">VIII. Another Argument for Conceſſions in the Ceremonies; ſeveral of our Eminent Men in Queen <hi>Elizabeths</hi> Reign were for the taking of them away, as their Letters to <hi>Bullinger</hi> inform us, mentioned by the Biſhop of <hi>Salisbury</hi> in his Travels; Letters of things remarkable in <hi>Switzerland, &amp;c.</hi> by Dr. <hi>Burnet</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Salisbury,</hi> tell us, that there is a vaſt Collection of Letters at <hi>Zurich,</hi> written either to <hi>Bul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linger</hi> or by him. Biſhop <hi>Jewel</hi> in a Letter, <hi>Feb.</hi> 8. 1566. wiſhes that the Veſtments together with all the other Remnants of Popery, might be thrown both out of their Churches, and out of the minds
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:100559:36"/>of the People, and laments the Queens fixedneſs to them: So that ſhe would ſuffer no change to be made. And in <hi>January</hi> the ſame year, <hi>Sands</hi> Archbiſhop of <hi>York</hi> writes, <hi>Contenditur de Veſtibus Papiſticis utendis vel non utendis, dabit Deus his quoque finem.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Horn</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Wincheſter,</hi> in a Letter, <hi>July</hi> 16. 1565. He writes of the Act concerning the Habits with great regret, and expreſſes ſome hopes that it might be Repealed next Seſſion of Parliament, if the Popiſh Party did not hinder it, and he ſeems to ſtand in doubt, whether he ſhould Conform himſelf to it or not, upon which he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires <hi>Bullingers</hi> advice. And in many Letters writ on that Subject, it is aſſerted, that both <hi>Crannier</hi> and <hi>Ridley</hi> intended to procure an Act for aboliſhing the Habits, and that they only defended their Lawful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, but not their fitneſs, and therefore they blamed private perſons that refuſed to obey the Laws.</p>
            <p>Biſhop <hi>Grindal</hi> in a Letter, <hi>Aug.</hi> 27. 1556. writes, that all the Biſhops, who had been beyond Sea, had at their return dealt with the Queen to let the matter of the Habits fall; but ſhe continued inflexi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. He laments the ill effects of the oppoſition that ſome had made to them, which had extreamly irritated the Queens Spirit. <hi>Cox</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Ely</hi> laments the averſion that they found in the Parliament to all the Propoſitions that were made for the Reformation of abuſes.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Peter Martyr</hi> to Biſhop <hi>Hooper;</hi> At firſt I conceived no ſmall joy of your ſingular and earneſt ſtudy, in that you put your endeavour that Chriſt his Religion may be brought again unto a chaſt and ſimple Purity. For what ſhould be more deſired of all Godly hearts, then that all things by little and little ſhould be clean taken away, and cut off, which have very little or nothing in them that can be referred wholly to Edification, but rather be judged of the Godly to be ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluous.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Homily of Faſting,</hi> Part 1. p. 172, 173. Edit. 1673. Gods Church ought not, neither may it be ſo tyed to that, (<hi>i. e.</hi> Faſting) or any other Order now made, or hereafter to be made and deviſed by the Authority of Man, but that it may Lawfully for juſt cauſes, alter, change or mitigate thoſe Eccleſiaſtical Decrees and Orders; yea, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cede wholly from them, and break them, when they tend either to Superſtition and Impiety, when they draw people from God, rather than work any edification in them. This Authority to mitigate Laws and Decrees Eccleſiaſtical the Apoſtles practiſed, ſignifying <hi>Acts</hi> 15. they would not lay any other burden upon them than theſe neceſſaries.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="65" facs="tcp:100559:36"/>
King <hi>Charles</hi> I. in his Declaration, with the Advice of his Privy Council, <hi>Jan.</hi> 1641. As for differences among our ſelves for matters indifferent in their own nature, we ſhall in tenderneſs to any number of our Loving Subjects very willingly comply with the Advice of our Parliament, that ſome Law may be made for the exemption of ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Conſciences from Puniſhment or Proſecution for ſuch Ceremonies (in ſuch caſes) which in the judgment of moſt men are held to be matters indifferent, and of ſome to be abſolutely unlawful.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Biſhop of</hi> Cork <hi>and</hi> Roſs<hi>'s Proteſtant Peacemaker.</hi> Some Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantials may be on our ſide abated, and had been doubtleſs long ago, if men of eager and inflexible Spirits had not hindered.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Dr.</hi> Goods <hi>Firmianus &amp; Dubit.</hi> p. 153. Some Wiſe and Peaceable Men have deſired that the uſe of certain Ceremonies might be forborn at leaſt for a time, which not withſtanding they are ſtill continued. Theſe Peaceable Men do abhor the great ſin of Separation, and do continue their Conformity.</p>
            <p>Dr. <hi>Stillingfleet</hi> alſo in Preface to <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nreaſonableneſs of Separation.</hi> Mr. <hi>Claud</hi> of <hi>France,</hi> Mr. <hi>De L' Angle. &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ceremonies to be left free.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Canons made</hi> 1640. Can. 7. In the Practice or Omiſſion of this Rite [bowing towards the Altar] we deſire that the Rule of Charity preſcribed by the Apoſtle may be obſerved, which is, that they which uſe this Rite, deſpiſe not them who uſe it not, and that they who uſe it not, condemn not thoſe that uſe it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Biſhop</hi> Bilſon <hi>of Subjection,</hi> Part 4. p. 15. Strangers are ſuffered in their Churches to retain their own Ceremonies, as be neither againſt Faith and good Manners; and therefore may be born in Chriſtian Unity, without offence or confuſion.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Letter to</hi> Johannes a Laſco <hi>concerning the uſe of ſuch Signs:</hi> It is ſurely the part of Brotherly Charity commanded us by God, to leave the uſe of thoſe Signs free to the Judgment and Conſcience of the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation, except we ſee an open abuſe either of Superſtition, or of Contention, (as if they diſpleaſed the greater and better part of the Church). It was evident at St. <hi>Pauls</hi> time by the moſt clear Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures of God, that the uſe of days, meats, and all other external things, was made free, and it was a ſure token of infirmity of Faith to doubt thereof.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="66" facs="tcp:100559:37"/>
               <hi>Lord</hi> Bacon <hi>in his Conſiderat. Dedicat. to K.</hi> James I. For the Cap and Surplice, ſince they be things in their nature indifferent, and yet by ſome held Superſtitious; and that the Queſtion is between Science and Conſcience, it ſeemeth to fall within the compaſs of the Apoſtles Rule, which is that the ſtronger deſcend and yield to the weaker, on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the difference is, that it will be materially ſaid, that the Rule holds between a private man and a private man, and not between the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience of a private man and the order of a Church. But yet ſith the Queſtion at this time is of a Toleration, not by connivance, which may encourage diſobedience, but by Law which may give a Liberty; it is good again to be adviſed, whether it fall not within the equity of the former Rule? And for ſubſcription if ſeemeth to be in the nature of a Confeſſion, and therefore proper to bind in the unity of Faith, and to be urged rather for Articles of Doctrine, than for Rites and Ceremonies, and points of outward concernment. For howſoever Politick Conſiderations and Reaſons of State may require Uniformity, yet Chriſtian and Divine grounds look chiefly upon Unity.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Dr.</hi> Edw. Bulkleys <hi>Apol. for the Religion Eſtabliſhed,</hi> Edit. 1608. p. 112. Touching the uſe of Surplices, Organs, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> in Divine Service; I ſay that men may differ in Opinions of theſe things, and agree in unity of Faith and Knowledge of the Son of God.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Doctor</hi> Fuller <hi>in his Appeal of injured Innocence, in defence of his Church History;</hi> Multiformity in things meerly indifferent with mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual Charity, doth more promote Gods Glory then Uniformity it ſelf.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Doctor</hi> Mores <hi>Mystery of Godlineſs,</hi> Sect. 10. Pref. About the Communion; I confeſs an Uniformity would look better in outward ſhew, but is not worth the leaſt ſtir and violence in diverſities of acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, or rather circumſtances interpretable to ſo good a meaning, as either Kneeling or Sitting at the Communion is; and the real exerciſe of Charity in leaving every one free is every whit as ſuitable to this ſolemn performance, as the moſt exquiſite Uniformity, if devoid of the Spirit of Meekneſs, and mutual forbearance. <hi>Item, To the ſame purpoſe about the Croſs:</hi> Unity of Hearts being better than Unifor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity in Actions indifferent, there ought to be no breach nor quarrel about theſe things: By an high value of the indiſpenſables of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity, and of the tender regard to the Conſciences of men, the Miniſter will conciliate more authority to himſelf, than if he drew too hard to an uniform complyance in things where Chriſt hath left us free.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="67" facs="tcp:100559:37"/>
               <hi>True ſtate of the Primitive Church,</hi> p 20. Let us be men of un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding, men in Devotion, be zealous, and hold faſt the ſubſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial parts of Religion, and let us leave it to Women and Children to contend about Ceremonies. Let it be indifferent to us, whether this or that, or no Ceremony, whether Kneel or not Kneel, Bow or not Bow, Surplice or no Surplice, Croſs or no Croſs, Ring or no Ring. Let us give Glory to God in all, and no offence to our Brethren in any thing.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Doctor</hi> Stillingfleets <hi>Irenicum,</hi> p. 65. He muſt be a great ſtranger in the Primitive Church, that takes not notice of the great diverſity of Rites and Cuſtoms uſed in particular Churches, without cenſuring of thoſe that differ'd from them; or if any by inconſiderate Zeal did proceed ſo far, how ill it was repreſented by other Chriſtians. And he concludes <hi>with that Divine Aphoriſm of St.</hi> Auſtin; <hi>Indignum <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſr ut propter ea quae nos Deo neque digniores,</hi> &amp;c. It is an unworthy thing for Chriſtians to condemn and judge one another for thoſe things which do not commend us unto God. To the ſame purpoſe in <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reaſonableneſs of Separation,</hi> That the Croſs be left at liberty, as the Parents deſire it, or wholly taken away, <hi>Pref. p.</hi> 83. <hi>Edit.</hi> 3.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>King</hi> Charles II. <hi>Declaration at</hi> Breda: Agreed to leave the Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies at liberty.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Dr.</hi> Rudde <hi>Biſhop of St.</hi> Davids <hi>Speech in the Convocation,</hi> 1604. In the life time of the late Archbiſhop (then <hi>Whitgift</hi>) theſe things were not ſo extreamly urged, but that many Learned Preachers en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyed their Liberty therein conditionally, that they did not by word nor deed diſgrace or diſturb the State eſtabliſhed.—</p>
            <p>
               <hi>King</hi> Charles II. <hi>Declaration from</hi> Breda. None ſhall be denied the Lords Supper for not Kneeling; none compelled to uſe the Croſs; it ſhall be Lawful to him that deſires to uſe the Croſs, to have ſuch Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters as will uſe it; and if the proper Miniſter refuſe, to get ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. None compell'd to bow at the name of Jeſus. The Surplice left to liberty, except in the Royal Chappel, Cathedrals, and Univerſities.</p>
            <p>Another <hi>Argument.</hi> The miſchief to the Church hath been very great from theſe Ceremonies, eſpecially from the Croſs.</p>
            <p>Firſt as to the Impoſition; though the preſent Fathers of the Church have ſignified their conſent unto a due liberty to Diſſenters, and ſome Indulgence to them beyond their Predeceſſors, yet ſeveral Miniſters in Queen <hi>Elizabeths,</hi> and King <hi>James</hi> I. Reign, and that of King <hi>Charles</hi> I. and at King <hi>Charles</hi> II. Return, have been turned out of
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:100559:38"/>their Benefices, and ſilenced for Nonconformity to theſe Ceremonies, although the Church of <hi>England</hi> confeſſeth them to be but things in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different. And it were hard, for refuſing upon a Conſcientious ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count to ſubmit to things indifferent, to have one of the greateſt pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhments inflicted on a man, Suſpenſion and Deprivation; even as Conformiſts would (many of them) think it hard to be Silenced for not aſſenting to the Perſeverance of the Saints, or any other of the five points, according to the common ſenſe or notion of our Diſſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Brethren.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Theſe Ceremonies have been as it were a bone of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention, thrown in between Conformiſts and Nonconformiſts. <hi>Zan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chies</hi> Letter to Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi> 1571. tells her; This Counſel about ſtrict Impoſition of Ceremonies will trouble the publick Peace of the Church, by cauſing contentions among men, and cauſe them to write Books one againſt another about things indifferent, which are the Golden Apples of Contention. Many an hot Diſpute and Conference there hath been, and Books wrote for and againſt them with bitter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Spirit; ſome contending as earneſtly about theſe indifferent things, as about matters of Faith; as if the very Life and Soul of Religion lay in them, and as if the cauſe of Chriſt and our Proteſtant Reformation were to ſtand or fall with them. The Ceremony of the Croſs hath been as vexatious to our Church, as ever the difference a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Ceremonies of Days and Meats was in the time of the Apoſtles, which occaſioned a Council at <hi>Jeruſalem, Acts</hi> 15. ſo many Chapters in St. <hi>Pauls</hi> Epiſtle, and ſuch contention among them.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, Much time hath been ſpent to little purpoſe or profit in Reading or Studying theſe matters. Oh the many that have wrote for and againſt! No little time doth it coſt men in Writing, as Biſhop <hi>Mourton,</hi> Dr. <hi>Bourges</hi> for; Dr. <hi>Ames</hi> againſt them and others; nay, every Book for or againſt Conformity, (as God knows there are abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of them upon theſe fruitleſs Controverſies) makes the Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies <hi>materiam contentionis</hi> matter of the Controverſie, and it calleth for a part and a conſiderable ſhare in the Book. Time alſo ſpent in Reading and Studying the point; and there muſt be Prayer to be led by the Spirit to find out the Truth for ſatisfaction. The time alſo which is ſpent in Preaching on this point, for it is commanded in the Canons: I ſay this rime would be much better ſpent in reading the Bible, with Comments or Treatiſes of Divinity, and ſo be Redeemed for Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, which now men are neceſſitated to ſpend for ſatisfaction herein.
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:100559:38"/>All this, a great deal, or a conſiderable portion of time may be better improved, if this Ceremony be taken away. And then as my Lord <hi>Bacons</hi> Eſſays, <hi>p.</hi> 13. <hi>Speaking of Peace in the Church;</hi> It turneth the labours of Writing and Reading Controverſies into Treatiſes of Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tification and Devotion.</p>
            <p>Again, The ſtrict exaction of theſe Ceremonies hath occaſioned ſome to cry them up, as if a conſiderable part of Miniſters Conformity to the Laws of God and Man lay therein, when in truth it is a very inconſiderable part. And ſome have ſought to get into favour with greater Perſons, and attain Preferment by a niceneſs and ſtrict obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance of every Punctilio about the Ceremonies, exacting perhaps a more ſtrict Obedience to theſe than to the Laws of God. And he ſhall paſs for an obedient and very good Son of the Church with ſome, that is a zealous ſtickler for theſe, though he be looſe in his Life, formal in his Religion, and uncharitable to thoſe that differ from him.</p>
            <p>Again, Some have declared that they Cannot joyn with us in Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſm, ſuffering their Children to be Baptized by Conforming Miniſters, becauſe of the Sign of the Croſs which they in their Conſciences can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not allow of; nor joyn in the Lords Supper becauſe of Kneeling, which ſeems to them (though through great weakneſs, and a more unreaſonable prejudice, when the Rubrick is ſo expreſly againſt the Idolatry and Adoration of the Sacramental Bread) a ſymbolizing with Idolaters, which things have bred no ſmall perplexity of mind and outward trouble to ſome Godly Perſons, ſaid Mr. <hi>Sprint</hi> in his days, <hi>Caſſ. Anglic.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I ſhall conclude this with <hi>Dr.</hi> Preſton <hi>on the Lords Prayer,</hi> p. 89. <hi>Thy Kingdom come:</hi> We intreat the Lord that he would curſe and croſs all Antichriſtian Plots and Practices; and we are to Pray againſt all lets and ſtumbling blocks that would hinder the proceedings of the Goſpel; that he would abandon all things that do offend, even all Remnants and Reliques of Superſtition, and ſuch Ceremonies as do but enſnare the Conſciences of men, and draw a great many into Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution and Trouble.</p>
            <p>A Second Miſchief to the Church hath been great in reſpect of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formiſts blind ſubmiſſion to this Ceremony. One not long before I en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred into the Miniſtry, and who lived in the ſame Pariſh where Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence placed me afterwards, when Dying lay under great troubles of his Conſcience for his Conformity, being bred up a Nonconformiſt. I have read in Mr. <hi>Sprints Caſſander Anglicanus</hi> of one or two more,
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:100559:39"/>not mentioned by name, as Conforming againſt their Conſciences with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſufficient ſatisfaction, have lamented it at laſt; as alſo of others, who have dyed very peaceably and comfortably, ſatisfied in their Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity. Some Conformiſts have certainly run into a wrong defence of this Ceremony, as Dedicating the Child unto the Service of him who dyed upon the Croſs, which is done in Baptiſm: And others have thought it above the peoples capacity. However, they may underſtand ſomewhat of what was ſaid before, and that Signing with the Croſs is none of their act and deed: Not they, but the Miniſter that is to wear the Surplice, and to Baptize, and Sign with the Croſs. The Miniſter is concerned to look to that, the Lawfulneſs of theſe. And Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> (as alſo <hi>Mr.</hi> Croftons <hi>Reformation no Separation,</hi> p. 24. <hi>Mr.</hi> Nyes <hi>Caſe of great uſe,</hi> p. 10. <hi>Mr.</hi> Balls <hi>Tryal of the grounds of Separation,</hi> p. 308. And the Author of a <hi>Diſcourſe of Scandal,</hi>) in his <hi>Chriſtian Directory</hi> among his Caſes of Conſcience hath reſolved it, that Parents diſſenting from it may ſuffer their children to be Signed with the Croſs after Baptiſm, declaring to the Miniſter in private, or their Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, that it was Baptiſm only that they deſired, and that they diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>owned the Sign of the Croſs, which they held to be unlawful. So that Parents are neither bound to the perſonal practice of it, nor to the profeſſion of its Lawfulneſs.</p>
            <p>And this appears to have been the Judgment and concurrent Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice of the Nonconformiſts of former times, who conſtantly joyned in the Prayers and other Acts of Worſhip, although they ſcrupled ſome Particular Ceremonies. All that we deſire is to have the Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of our Conſciences allowed us in that which is not theirs, but ours to practiſe. And if there be offence given, it is not from us, (ſaid Dr. <hi>Saunderſon</hi> in his <hi>Treatiſe of Scandal;</hi>) or at leaſt not ſo much (in the preſent caſe of the Church) there being a neceſſity laid upon us as to the uſe of it, if our Conſciences be ſatisfied therein: So that whatever we would do, if it were left to our Liberty to uſe or for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bear it, ſince we are not allowed to exerciſe our Miniſtry otherwiſe than upon Conformity to it, it is Prudentially good, and Spiritually neceſſary for us to Conform to it, even in the Judgment of the Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med Churches abroad, <hi>Geneva,</hi> as <hi>Beza, Colladonus, Goulartius, Franciſcus Port, Henricus Stephanus</hi> declared in a Letter ſent to the Brethren in <hi>England,</hi> that were unſatisfied in their Conformity to this Ceremony, and deſired to know their Judgment. And ſo have the late Miniſters in <hi>France,</hi> as Mr. <hi>Daille,</hi> Mr. <hi>Claud,</hi> Mr. <hi>De L' Angle</hi>
               <pb n="71" facs="tcp:100559:39"/>tells us in his Letter; My Opinion in this matter is the ſame that is held by our Churches. Mr. <hi>Calvin</hi> ſeemed to look upon it as tolera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and to be born with, <hi>Zancy</hi> and others, though they did not fully approve of the Impoſition.</p>
            <p n="3">III. <hi>Miſchief,</hi> In reſpect of the cenſoriouſneſs of ſome Separatiſts, inveighing againſt theſe Ceremonies as Limbs of Antichriſt, reliques of Popery, Additions, Superſtitious, will Worſhip, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> as before in the Objections againſt them, condemning (as my Lord <hi>Hales</hi> in his Diſcourſe of Religion calls them) theſe blameleſs Ceremonies as con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidently, as if they were infallibly aſſured of their unlawfulneſs, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viling and cenſuring the Men that uſe them, as if he could not be a good Man that ſubmitteth to the Ceremonies, but muſt needs conform to them againſt his Conſcience out of Complyance with the Government, and for his Preferment ſake. It is hard for Miniſters who ſubmit to theſe things according to their Conſciences, though it be with great Charity and Moderation to thoſe that differ from them, to be termed Time-ſervers, Formaliſts, Luke-warm, Men wanting the Power of Godlineſs, as ſome conceited Perſons, who have more Heat than Light, more Zeal than Knowledge, do not ſtick to affirm. Sure this becometh not Chriſtian Charity, in 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.4. Charity vaunteth not it ſelf, is not puffed up (with a conceit of its own Judgment, as if it were infallible, and they muſt needs be in the right.) Again Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity thinketh no Evil, and doth not behave it ſelf unſeemly. But ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly if we judge of their thinking by their evil ſpeaking, and unſeemly deportment towards their Governours, and others, there muſt be an abundance of cenſoriouſneſs in the Heart; <hi>For out of the abundance of the heart the mouth ſpeaketh.</hi> In 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.12. You there read of thoſe that ſpeak evil of things they underſtand not, applicable to theſe Men. Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> ſaith thus in his Book of <hi>Church-Government;</hi> Of all our Ceremonies there is none that I have ſuſpected more to be ſimply unlawful than the Croſs, yet dare not I peremptorily ſay, that it is unlawful; nor will I condemn either Ancients or Moderns that uſe it; nor will I make any diſturbance in the Church about it, any farther than my own forbearance of it. And thoſe Grave Men at the Grand Debate; it being doubtful whether God hath given Men power to inſtitute ſuch Myſtical Teaching Signs, as being not neceſſary in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral, fall not under the particular Rules, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> They are by ſome held ſinful and unlawful in themſelves, [by ſome not as of another Judgment it ſeems] by others very inconvenient, and unſuitable to the ſimplicity of the Goſpel-Worſhip, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> p. 9. <hi>Of the Grand De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate.</hi>
               <pb n="72" facs="tcp:100559:40"/>But the new Generation of Diſſenters are grown wiſer than the Grave, Aged, and Judicious (that ſpeak more modeſtly, leaving the lawfulneſs of it as doubtful and <hi>ſub Judice</hi>) and ſeem to wonder at thoſe before them, that they ſhould ſee no farther, not to the ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter unlawfulneſs of theſe Ceremonies, and ſome of the Prayers too, which they ſay, they ſee as clear as the Light to be Popiſh and Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſtian, and againſt Scripture. I profeſs that the Objections are ſo many, and the ill Circumſtances that attend its uſe at preſent, that after all I dare not be poſitive and peremptory that it is lawful; nor will I be over-confident, charitably allowing my Brethren their Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty to diſſent, and deſiring the like Charity from them, as to my own Conformity upon prevailing probable Arguments; leaving it to God who only is Infallible, to decide the Caſe at the day of Judgment: Where I truſt his Mercy will pardon me if I have erred, as ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving ſought for the Spirit to guide me into Truth, and as having alſo the Ancient Church, and the Modern Reformed Forreign Divines ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probation of Conformity thereunto.</p>
            <p>It is from the ſtrict and ſevere Impoſition, the blind ſubmiſſion of others, not being able to give any tolerable account of it to their Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, nor Anſwer Objections againſt it: And from the cenſoriouſneſs, and ill Names that have been given this Ceremony of the Croſs, that they have brought ſuch an Odium upon it, and wrought ſuch an ill Opinion in our Conforming People againſt it. Further they hate Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery, and Papiſts uſe this ſo much, and abuſe it to Idolatry and Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtition, that they hate and diſguſt the uſe of it upon that account. I know our Governours never intended to make us Odious in the Eyes of the People, but I am ſure there could ſcarce be a more effectual way and means to do it, than by enjoyning theſe things ſo ſtrictly, the which People are ſo much ſet againſt, that they diſaffect thoſe that uſe them; and the Governours that impoſe them even againſt the guſt of the Congregation. If there had not been a little of the old grudge in ſome at the Grand Debate, ſure they had been yielded up then, and not have remained unto this day troubling the peace of the Church.</p>
            <p>I ſhall conclude with the common Aſſertion of the Reformed Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, That all Churches ſhould labour as much as poſſible may be, after Apoſtolical ſimplicity, and fewneſs of Ceremonies, which they judge the ſafeſt, the pureſt, and the beſt, as <hi>Peter Martyr, Bucer, Calvin, Beza, Zanchy,</hi> and indeed almoſt all good Men affirm.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:100559:40"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
